<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations of man's mortalitie. Or, A way to true blessednesse. Written, by Mrs. Alice Sutcliffe wife of Iohn Sutcliffe Esquire, groome of his Maiesties most honourable privie chamber</title>
            <author>Sutcliffe, Alice.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13154)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18516)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1010:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations of man's mortalitie. Or, A way to true blessednesse. Written, by Mrs. Alice Sutcliffe wife of Iohn Sutcliffe Esquire, groome of his Maiesties most honourable privie chamber</title>
                  <author>Sutcliffe, Alice.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[40], 200 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas] F[awcet] for Henry Seyle at the Tygers head in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A a¹²  B-I¹²  K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Meditations of mans mortality.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Meditations OF MAN'S MORTALITIE. <hi>OR,</hi> A WAY TO TRVE Bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. ALICE SVTCLIFFE wife of <hi>Iohn Sutcliffe</hi> Eſquire, Groome of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Privie Chamber.</p>
            <p>The Second EDITION, enlarged.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The wages of Sinne is Death, but the guift of GOD, is Eternall life, through <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> our Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> and <hi>T. F.</hi> for <hi>Henry Seyle</hi> at the <hi>Tygers</hi> head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS AND GRACIOVS PRINCESSE, <hi>KATHERINE</hi> DVTCHESSE OF BVCKINGHAM:
<pb facs="tcp:18516:3"/> AND THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERTVOVS LADY, <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SANNA,</hi> COVNTESSE OF DENBEIGH her Siſter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gracious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I read how the Gods ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of a Handfull of <hi>Franken-ſence</hi> offered by pure <hi>Devotion,</hi> then whole Hecatombes of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Spices in <hi>Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> I am incouraged, having duely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:18516:4"/>Your unlimited Goodneſſe, to preſent this my Mite unto your <hi>Grace,</hi> and your Honourable <hi>Siſter,</hi> For as you are Twinnes in <hi>Virtues,</hi> ſo I have joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned You in my <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> Where firſt, I moſt humbly crave of You to paſſe a favourable <hi>Cenſure</hi> of my procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, it beeing, I know not uſuall for a <hi>Woman</hi> to doe ſuch things: Yet ELIHA ſayth, <hi>There is a Spirit in Man, and the inſpiration of the Almightie giveth them
<pb facs="tcp:18516:4"/>Vnderſtanding.</hi> And it is ſayd againe: <hi>Out of the mouthes of Babes and Sucklings, thou ſhalt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Praiſe.</hi> I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I ſhall meet with mocking <hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> that will carpe at <hi>Goodneſſe;</hi> wherefore, I runne to Your ſelves for <hi>refuge;</hi> humbly craving to bee aſſiſted by your <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as the Splendant <hi>Sunne</hi> to diſperſe thoſe <hi>Miſts.</hi> I have choſen a <hi>ſubiect</hi> not altogether <hi>Pleaſing;</hi> but my ayme
<pb facs="tcp:18516:5"/>is, that it may prove <hi>Profitable,</hi> having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in this ſhort courſe of my Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, how apt <hi>Man</hi> is, not to thinke of his <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> which ſtealeth upon him as a <hi>Thiefe in the night:</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth mee, that there is no <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> wiſely undertaken, whereof the <hi>End</hi> is not fore-caſted, in the firſt place, howſoever it bee laſt put in execution; I have ever accompted <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> to be like
<pb facs="tcp:18516:5"/>a <hi>Beast,</hi> who having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>benefites,</hi> thinkes not of any <hi>acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Owing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a due Debt of <hi>Thankefulneſſe</hi> for Your unexpreſſable undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Favours,</hi> and being no wayes able to cauſe the deſires of my Heart to appeare <hi>worthy</hi>-your <hi>Acceptances,</hi> I have made choyſe of this, as being perſwaded thereto, by that truely Noble ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes which hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently appeared in You, to the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:18516:6"/>of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that heere it may find <hi>admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> which otherwiſe might want <hi>Entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and for that you have beene more then a <hi>Mother</hi> to mee. I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely from her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived life, but next under God from your Grace, &amp; your honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Siſter</hi> the being both of mee and mine. By which as there is none greater then your <hi>Selfe</hi> to whom in duty I am bound, ſo there is not any to whom I wiſh greater Proſperity both
<pb facs="tcp:18516:6"/>for <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> bleſſings, then to your Grace; beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to preſerve you and your Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Off-ſpring here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, with my no leſſe vertuous Lady your <hi>Siſter,</hi> to whom I am tyed by the ſame bonds of <hi>Thankfulneſſe,</hi> that as God hath made your <hi>Renownes</hi> great up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, ſo I beſeech him to adde to your <hi>Lives</hi> length of dayes, and after life, Eternall happineſſe in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
<pb facs="tcp:18516:7"/>whither CHRIST is gone to prepare a place for You. I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remayning,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces, and your Honors truely devoted Servant,</hi> Alice Sutcliffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ACCROSTIQVE,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Renowned Name of the moſt vertuous Princeſſe, <hi>KATHERINE</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:8"/>
            <l> KNow you this Princeſſe, BVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KINGHAM'S Chaſt Dutcheſſe?</l>
            <l>ASke aged Time with his worm-eaten Crutches,</l>
            <l>TO find amongſt the numbers of his Role</l>
            <l>HEr-Paralell, of ſuch a Heavenly moule,</l>
            <l>EXcelling ſo i'th' beauties of the Soule:</l>
            <l>RIch in all Treaſures, that to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue tend:</l>
            <l>IN Faith, Hope, Charity; the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed's end.</l>
            <l>NOr is there ought, that lives in Woman kinde:</l>
            <l>EXceeding the rare proweſse of her Minde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:8"/>
            <l>BOrne of High blood, from RVT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LANDS Family:</l>
            <l>VNited to a Duke of Royall ſtate.</l>
            <l>CVrs'd bee the time, more curs'd his cruelty</l>
            <l>KIll'd him; and reav'd this Turtle of her mate,</l>
            <l>IN peerleſſe woe, we ſtill lament that fate:</l>
            <l>NOr ſhall his memorie e're out of date.</l>
            <l>GOe on then Gracious Princeſſe, grac't by Fame,</l>
            <l>HOnour ſhall ſtill, attend your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Name:</l>
            <l>ANd as your Goodneſſe hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, ſo</l>
            <l>MAy Heaven the greateſt good on You beſtow.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:9"/>
            <head>AN ACCROSTIQVE, Vpon the Name of the Right Honourable, and truely vertuous Lady; SVSANNA, Counteſſe of <hi>Denheigh.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>SEe heere a Lady, bleſſed in her birth,</l>
            <l>VNto whoſe Greatneſſe, Goodnes ioyn'd is ſtill</l>
            <l>SVSANNA ne're ſo famous was on Earth</l>
            <l>AS is this Lady, lead by vertuous will,</l>
            <l>NOthing ſo ſweete to her, as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly mirth,</l>
            <l>NO Muſike ſounds like <hi>Haleluia</hi> ſtill</l>
            <l>A Happy Soule, which thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights doth fill</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:9"/>
            <l>DAigne then to view theſe lines, where truely I</l>
            <l>EXpreſſe but truth, not vſing Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery:</l>
            <l>NO Fallaces within my mouth once lurkes,</l>
            <l>BVt hates all thoſe, that uſe diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling workes.</l>
            <l>EVen as your Goodneſſe merits, ſo ſpeake I</l>
            <l>I Am your Servant, bound untill I dye</l>
            <l>GIve leave, then gracious Lady, for I finde,</l>
            <l>HEaven hath indu'd you, with a vertuous minde.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ACCROSTIQVE,</hi> Vpon the name and Titles of the <hi>Right honourable and my ever</hi> honored Lord, <hi>PHILIP</hi> Earle <hi>of</hi> Pembrooke <hi>and</hi> Montgomery, <hi>Lord Chamberlaine of his</hi> Majeſties Houſhold, &amp;c.</head>
            <l>PEMBROOKE's great Peere, your Princely favour I</l>
            <l>HEere humbly crave, to guerdon my weake pen,</l>
            <l>IF this doth ſhow my imbeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</l>
            <l>LIke a good Patron, ſhroud it from bad men</l>
            <l>I By your favours mov'd doe this preſent,</l>
            <l>PRay then my Lord, accept my good intent,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:10"/>
            <l>POore are my weake endeavours, yet if you,</l>
            <l>ENcourage my <hi>Minervaes</hi> infant Muſe</l>
            <l>MY cheriſht thoughts, by that, may frame anew</l>
            <l>BOoke of true thanks, unto your Lordſhips uſe:</l>
            <l>RIght Noble then, view but the vertuous tract,</l>
            <l>OF this ſmall Volume, and if you ſhall finde,</l>
            <l>OVght good expreſſed, by our Sexes act,</l>
            <l>KNow honor'd Lord, my ſtarres are very kinde,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:11"/>
            <l>MOVNTGOMERY, my Caelique Muſe doth mount</l>
            <l>ON Cherubs wing, from this low Orbe to heaven,</l>
            <l>VErtue is here expreſt, vices account;</l>
            <l>NOr is't a Tale, or Fable that is given</l>
            <l>TRuth never is aſham'd to ſhew it's face:</l>
            <l>GReat man and good, but alwayes loves the light.</l>
            <l>OMay it then, find an accepted Grace</l>
            <l>MOre cauſe a woman, did the ſame indite,</l>
            <l>EVen then as DERORAH's ſweet tuned ſong,</l>
            <l>— Run;</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:11"/>
            <l>RVng out her ſacred Peale, in holy Writ:</l>
            <l>OSo, I pray my heart, my pen, my tongue,</l>
            <l>YEa all my faculties, may follow it:</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips Devoted Servant,</hi> Alice Sutcliffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:12"/>
            <head>TO Mrs. <hi>Alice Sutcliffe,</hi> on her divine Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</head>
            <l>WHen I had read</l>
            <l>your holy <hi>Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And in them view'd</l>
            <l>th' <hi>uncertainty</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>motives,</hi> and true <hi>Spurres</hi>
            </l>
            <l>to all good <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>and the <hi>Godly</hi>'s ſtrife,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Danger</hi> of <hi>delaying</hi>
            </l>
            <l>to <hi>Repent,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And the <hi>deceipt</hi> of <hi>pleaſures,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>by <hi>Conſent.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:12"/>
            <l>The <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort</hi> of weake <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>with their <hi>warning,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>From fearefull <hi>back-ſlides;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And the debt we' are in,</l>
            <l>To follow <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>by our owne diſcerning</l>
            <l>Our great <hi>reward,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>th' <hi>aeternall Crown</hi> to win.</l>
            <l>I ſayd, who' had ſupp'd ſo deepe</l>
            <l>of this ſweet <hi>Chalice,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Muſt <hi>CELIA</hi> bee,</l>
            <l>the <hi>Anagram</hi> of <hi>ALICE.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ben. Ionſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:13"/>
            <head>Vpon the Religious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of Mrs. ALICE SVTCLIFFE.</head>
            <head type="sub">TO THE READER.</head>
            <l>WOuld'ſt thou</l>
            <l>(fraile Reader) thy</l>
            <l>true Nature ſee?</l>
            <l>Behold this Glaſſe</l>
            <l>of thy Mortality.</l>
            <l>Digeſt the precepts</l>
            <l>of this pious Booke,</l>
            <l>Thou canſt not in</l>
            <l>a nobler Mirrour looke.</l>
            <l>Though ſad it ſeeme,</l>
            <l>and may looſe mirth deſtroy,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:13"/>
            <l>That is not ſad</l>
            <l>which leades to perfect ioy.</l>
            <l>Thanke her faire Soule</l>
            <l>whoſe meditation makes</l>
            <l>Thee ſee thy frailtie;</l>
            <l>nor diſdaine to take</l>
            <l>That knowledge, which</l>
            <l>a Womans skill can bring.</l>
            <l>All are not <hi>Syren</hi>-notes</l>
            <l>that women ſing.</l>
            <l>How true that Sexe can write,</l>
            <l>how grave, how well,</l>
            <l>Let all the Muſes,</l>
            <l>and the Graces tell.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: MA</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:14"/>
            <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN SVTCLIFFE <abbr>Eſq</abbr> upon the receipt of this Booke written by his Wife.</head>
            <l>SIr, I receiv'd your Booke</l>
            <l>with acceptation,</l>
            <l>And, thus returne</l>
            <l>a due congratulation,</l>
            <l>For that good Fortune,</l>
            <l>which hath bleſt your life</l>
            <l>By making you</l>
            <l>the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Wife.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Although I neuer ſaw her,</l>
            <l>yet I ſee,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Fruit,</hi> and by the <hi>Fruit</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I judge the <hi>Free.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>My Praiſe addes nothing to it:</l>
            <l>That which is</l>
            <l>Well done, can praiſe it ſelfe;</l>
            <l>and ſo may this.</l>
            <l>To be a woman, 'tis enough with me,</l>
            <l>To merit praiſe;</l>
            <l>For I can never be</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:14"/>
            <l>So much their <hi>Friend,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>as they have heretofore</l>
            <l>Deſerv'd; although</l>
            <l>they merited no more.</l>
            <l>When, therefore</l>
            <l>to their <hi>Woman-hood</hi> I finde</l>
            <l>The love of ſacred</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Piety</hi> conioyn'd,</l>
            <l>Me thinks I have</l>
            <l>my duty much forgot,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe I praiſe</l>
            <l>(although I know them not)</l>
            <l>But, when to <hi>Woman-hood</hi>
            </l>
            <l>and good <hi>Affections,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thoſe rare <hi>Abilities,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>and thoſe <hi>Perfections,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Vnited are,</l>
            <l>to which our <hi>Sexe</hi> aſpire,</l>
            <l>Then, forc'd I am</l>
            <l>to <hi>Love,</hi> and to <hi>admire.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I am not of their mind,</l>
            <l>who if they ſee,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:15"/>
            <l>Some <hi>Female-Studies</hi>
            </l>
            <l>fairely ripened be,</l>
            <l>(With Maſculine ſucceſſe)</l>
            <l>doe peeviſhly,</l>
            <l>Their worths due honour</l>
            <l>unto them deny,</l>
            <l>By overſtrictly</l>
            <l>cenſuring the ſame;</l>
            <l>Or doubting whether</l>
            <l>from themſelves it came,</l>
            <l>For, well I know.</l>
            <l>Dame <hi>Pallas</hi> and the <hi>Muſes,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Into that <hi>Sexe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>their faculties infuſes,</l>
            <l>As freely as to <hi>Men;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>and they that know,</l>
            <l>How to improve their <hi>Guift,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>ſhall find it ſo.</l>
            <l>Then ioy in your good Lot,</l>
            <l>and praiſes due</l>
            <l>To <hi>Him</hi> aſcribe, that thus</l>
            <l>hath honor'd you.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo. Withers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Vpon the Meditations of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.</hi> ALICE SVTCLIFFE.</head>
            <l>I Have no Muſe my owne,</l>
            <l>but what I ſee.</l>
            <l>Worthy of praiſe,</l>
            <l>that is a Muſe to me.</l>
            <l>Divinity (the higheſt theame)</l>
            <l>will find</l>
            <l>No fitter ſubiect</l>
            <l>then an humble mind,</l>
            <l>And as in ſcorne of them</l>
            <l>that are more fit</l>
            <l>By inſtruments leſſe notable</l>
            <l>expreſseth it.</l>
            <l>Almes and Devotion,</l>
            <l>Zeale and Charity.</l>
            <l>Might for thy Sexe</l>
            <l>beſeeming Scripture be,</l>
            <l>But when thou ſpeak'ſt</l>
            <l>of death, and that iuſt doome</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:16"/>
            <l>Which ſhall on all</l>
            <l>conditions, ages, come,</l>
            <l>And thence deſcending</l>
            <l>to Philoſophie,</l>
            <l>Teacheſt weake Nature</l>
            <l>how to learne to dye:</l>
            <l>It ſeemes to me</l>
            <l>above thy Sex and State,</l>
            <l>Some heavenly ſparke</l>
            <l>doth thee Illuminate.</l>
            <l>Live ſtill a praiſe,</l>
            <l>but no example to</l>
            <l>Others, to hope,</l>
            <l>as thou haſt done, to doe.</l>
            <l>Live ſtill thy ſexes honour,</l>
            <l>and when Death</l>
            <l>(With who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art acquainted)</l>
            <l>ſtoppes thy breath</l>
            <l>Fame to Poſteritie</l>
            <l>ſhall make thee ſhine</l>
            <l>And adde thy Name</l>
            <l>vnto the Muſes nine.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>PET: HEYVVOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:16"/>
            <head>AN ENCOMIVM <hi>vpon the Authoreſſe</hi> and Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GReat Ladies that to vertue</l>
               <l>are inclin'd,</l>
               <l>See here the pious practice</l>
               <l>of a wife,</l>
               <l>Expreſſed by the beauties</l>
               <l>of the Mind,</l>
               <l>And now ſet forth</l>
               <l>in Pictures of the life,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18516:17"/>
               <l>Wherein matter and forme</l>
               <l>are both at ſtrife</l>
               <l>Who ſhall be Maſter:</l>
               <l>but i'th end hands ſhooke,</l>
               <l>For that they have</l>
               <l>a Miſtreſſe to theyr Booke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe Language I muſt needs</l>
               <l>(in truth) admire,</l>
               <l>And how ſuch Elegance</l>
               <l>ſhould from her ſpring:</l>
               <l>Vntill I thinke of Zeale</l>
               <l>(that Caeliquefire)</l>
               <l>Which might tranſport her ſoule,</l>
               <l>by Cherubs wing</l>
               <l>In Proſe or Numbers,</l>
               <l>piouſly to ſing</l>
               <l>Precepts of Praiſe,</l>
               <l>worthy your approbation;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18516:17"/>
               <l>For ſhe is <hi>Rara Avis</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>in our Nation.</l>
               <l>And though her youth,</l>
               <l>gives her no <hi>SYBILS</hi> name</l>
               <l>Nor doth ſhe Prophecie,</l>
               <l>as they of old:</l>
               <l>Yet ſhe's indu'd</l>
               <l>with the moſt ſacred flame</l>
               <l>Of Poeſie Divine;</l>
               <l>and doth vnfold</l>
               <l>Nought but the truth,</l>
               <l>and therefore may be bold.</l>
               <l>Whoſe holy paines,</l>
               <l>and ſtudy here expreſt,</l>
               <l>Shall Regiſter her name</l>
               <l>amongſt the bleſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VRANIA,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>is her moſt heavenly Muſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18516:18"/>
               <l>Which flyeth vpwards,</l>
               <l>where her minde is placed.</l>
               <l>She ſings ſuch Songs,</l>
               <l>as <hi>DEEORAH</hi> did vſe.</l>
               <l>When ſhe, and <hi>BARVCH</hi>
               </l>
               <l>had their foes abaſed;</l>
               <l>For which, with Lawrell</l>
               <l>ſhee may well be graced.</l>
               <l>And ſtil'd the Paragon,</l>
               <l>of theſe our Times,</l>
               <l>In her ſweet Proſe,</l>
               <l>and true compoſed Rimes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thinke not Ladies</l>
               <l>that I doe contrive,</l>
               <l>Numbers to mend</l>
               <l>ought that is done amiſſe;</l>
               <l>Or that I meane,</l>
               <l>to keepe her name alive</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18516:18"/>
               <l>VVhen ſhe is gone:</l>
               <l>and paſs'd to greater bliſſe,</l>
               <l>For I ne're knew her,</l>
               <l>when I framed this.</l>
               <l>Onely I read her lines,</l>
               <l>which forc't me praiſe</l>
               <l>The Picture of her minde,</l>
               <l>with this courſe bayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRA: LENTON</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:19"/>
            <head>THE Contents of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>VVHerie the vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Mans life expreſſed, and of the fearefull end of the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Fol. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>II.</label>
               <item>Motiues and Jnducements to true Godlineſſe. <hi>Fol. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>III.</label>
               <item>Of the Peace of a good Conſcience, and the Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:18516:19"/>end of the godly. <hi>fol. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <label>IIII.</label>
               <item>Of the deferring of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, how dangerous it is, and of the deceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of Worldly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. <hi>fol. 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>Comforts for the weake Chriſtian, and to bee ware of Back-ſliding. <hi>fol. 101.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>VI.</label>
               <item>That man ought to bee wonne to follow Godlineſſe, in reſpect of the Eternall happineſſe. <hi>fol. 114.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:20"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18516:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS OF MANS Mortality.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Wherein the vncertainty of Mans life is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and of the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end of the Wicked.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I behold the Heavens &amp; the earth, the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of the Almighty, and ſee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all Creatures both for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18516:21"/>commodity and pleaſure, which as a ſtore-houſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all things for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe and benefit of Man: I cannot but vſe to my ſelfe, the ſaying of the Prophet DAVID;<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Lord! what is Man, that thou ſhouldeſt thinke on him; or the Sonne of man, that thou ſhouldeſt be mindfull of him, thou haſt made him but a little lower then the Angels; thou haſt crowned him with honour and worſhip; by reaſon of which, I thinke him to be onely happy and a God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth; and that there is no bleſſednes beyond this: but looking into him with more deliberation; I find
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18516:21"/>his breath is in his noſtrils, and that hee is as the Beaſt that periſheth;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> I find his wife to be but a ſpan, and the perpetuity of his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, no better then a flower, which flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to day, and to morrow is out downe and withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; and that his habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is but a Pilgrimage, hee hath no certaine abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I perceiue there is no building of Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles heere, this is no place of reſt. I remember the foole, that ſayd to his ſoule,<note place="margin">Luke, <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> There was much laid up for many yeares, but that night his ſoule was taken from him, and how that after Death hee muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18516:22"/>give an account of his Stewardſhip, for they are not his, but lent him of the Lord; neyther to abuſe through exceſſe, nor nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdice, but to put them foorth to the beſt vſe, and to the glory of him who is the giver of all good things.</p>
               <p>For it is true, that a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſayth; Hee that ſeeketh for true Happines in this world, followeth a ſhaddow, which when hee thinketh hee is ſureſt of, vaniſheth and is nothing; and the Apoſtle PAVL ſayth; If in this life wee were onely happie, wee were of all men moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18516:22"/>
               <p> Seeing then it is ſo,<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> That man which is borne of a woman hath but a ſhort time to liue, and that few and euill are the dayes of his Pilgrimage, pointed out but to Threeſcore and tenne, and if Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend him ſo farre, as to affoord him life till Foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore, yet is it ſo full of infirmities, that it becomes a burthen to him, Life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a briitle and miſerable fetter, which chaineth the pure and everlaſting ſoule, to the vile, ſinfull, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body.</p>
               <p>Yet where is hee, that takes the Wiſe mans counſell,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> To remember his Creator in the dayes of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18516:23"/>his Youth, before the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill day comes, and the time approach, in the which, he ſhall ſay; I have no pleaſure in them; for if a man live many yeares and rejoyce in them all, yet let him remember the dayes of Darknes, for they are many; the Sun ſets and riſeth againe; but thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, when thy glaſſe is run, and the ſhort gleame of thy Summers Sun is ſpent, ſhall never returne againe. How ſoone alas, is thy ſpan graſped, thy minute wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, thy flower dead, thy vapor of life gone; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thought, without dread eyther of ſinnes paſt, or accompts to come?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18516:23"/>Where is there one, that lookes into the eſtate of his Soule, with a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eye; that examines his conſcience, unvayleth his heart, and conſidereth his wayes, and how that he is every day of his life, a dayes journey nearer his end, and nothing is wanting for the expiration thereof, but the ſtroke of death, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in a moment; and then thou art gone, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to unexpreſſable end leſſe Ioyes, or caſeleſſe and endleſſe miſeries. For no ſooner art thou borne to poſſeſſe this World, but death iſſueth forth incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently out of his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, to finde thy life; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18516:24"/>doth he alwayes ſend his harbinger before to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thee with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but many times en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth unexpected, unloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for; and yet dareſt thou reſt in ſecurity, me thinkes it ſhould make thee tremble, were not thy conſcience ſeared; to think of the divineneſſe of that Iuſtice, before whom, thou art to ſtand, being in the day of his Wrath, and at the barre of his Iudgment: canſt thou thinke then, to bee able to indure his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry eye, whoſe ſight will pierce to the very centure of thy heart and ſoule, and rip up every fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred corner of thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18516:24"/>O then! bethinke thy ſelfe in time, before that gloomy day comes, that day of Cloudes and thicke darkeneſſe, that day of deſolation and confuſion approach; when all the Inhabitants of the Earth ſhall mourne and lament, and all faces ſhall gather blackneſſe. <hi>Joel.</hi> 2. Becauſe, the time of their Iudgment is come; alas! with what a fearefull hart and weeping eyes, and ſorrowfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling loynes, wilt thou at that laſt and great aſſize looke upon CHRIST IESVS, when he ſhall moſt gloriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, with innumerable Angels in flaming fire, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18516:25"/>render vengeance on them that know him not? What a cold dampe will ſeaze upon thy ſoule, when thou ſhalt behold him, whom thou haſt all thy life long, reiected in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, deſpiſed in his members, and neglected in his love: what horror and terror of ſpirit will poſſeſſe thee; how wilt thou cry to the Rockes and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fall upon thee, and cover thee from the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his Wrath; when thou ſhalt behold, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens burning, the Elements melting, the Earth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, the Sea roaring, the Sunne turne into darknes, and the Moone incobloud:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18516:25"/>how will thy numberleſſe ſinnes in hideous formes appeare before thee, every one of them bearing the Enſignes of Gods heavie diſpleaſure, dipped in a bloudy coloured dye; and crying out, for vengeance againſt thee: alas! if thy faultring tongue ſhould go about to faine ſome ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſhew of a colourable excuſe, how ſoone would it be ſtopped, all thy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both for thoughts, words, and deeds, being regiſtred in a booke, and kept within the Court of Heaven. Oh remember! how terrible his voyce was when he gave his Law to his choſen people, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18516:26"/>thou it will bee leſſe terrible, when he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand an account of that Law, which thou haſt ſo many times careleſly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Oh then, whether will his wrath carry thee, where will the blaſt of his breath hurry thee, it was thy ſins that inflamed his wrath, &amp; his wrath will inflame that fire which will never goe out: Oh then alas, whil'ſt thou haſt time, become thy own friend, looke into thy ſelfe, and by a ſerious exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, prove the Pilot of thy owne Ship, which now lyeth floating on the Seas of this troubleſome World, ballanc'd onely with cares, and diſquieting pleaſures of this life, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18516:26"/>how thou ſayl'ſt with a full courſe, towards the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of endleſſe Happines; yet one blaſt of unprepared death will turne thy ſayles, and plunge thee irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly into that bottomleſſe Guife, where one houres torment, will infinitely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all the pleaſures thy whole life contained: and wilt thou now ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very brim of Hell, melt in thy delights: Alas, ſlippery is thy footing, and thy hold but by the thread of life, which ſtretched to the length, ſoone crackes: yet how triflingly ſpendeſt thou thy pretious time, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out thy ſpirits, and robbing thine eyes of their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18516:27"/>beloved ſleepe, for thoſe things, to the which, the time will come, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remembrance of them will be bitter, and to the which, thou muſt bid an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting farewell.</p>
               <p>Yet not conſidering theſe things? how many are there, that only ſpend their time in jollity, and ſodainly goe downe to the Grave; they cry to themſelves; Peace, peace, when ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Deſtruction over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes them, not once thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of IEREMIA'S la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for <hi>Jernſalem;</hi> wherein hee complaines, That ſhee remembred not her laſt end.<note place="margin">Lamen. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Would they but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18516:27"/>that as the Tree fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſo it lyeth; and as Death leaves them, ſo ſhall Iudgement finde them; they would not draw Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with cords of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor ſinne as with cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes; did they thinke upon the reward of Sinne; did they conſider how full of griefe and miſery, how ſhort and tranſitorious this preſent life is, and the vaine Pleaſures thereof: how on every ſide, theyr enemies compaſſe them, and that Death lyeth in wayte againſt them, every where catching them ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly and unawares. Did that ſaying often ſound in theyr eares, <hi>Ariſe and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18516:28"/>come to Judgement,</hi> they would not deferre theyr Repentance to theyr laſt end, or their old-age; when it can not be ſayd, that they leave Sin, but ſinne them. Shall they offer to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, the World, and their owne fleſh, the flower and ſtrength of theyr yeares, and ſerve God with the lees and dregs:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> when the Prophet MALACHY com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned of the peoples e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Offerings, hee ſayd; Offer it now unto thy Governour, will hee be pleaſed with thee or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thy perſon: and can they thinke, this great GOD will bee pleaſed with them.<note place="margin">King. <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> If RABSHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHA
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18516:28"/>and HOLOFERNES,<note place="margin">Iudith. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> but Meſſengers for theyr Lords, tooke it ſo ill; that the Iewes came not forth to make theyr peace with them, that they threatned nothing ſhould pacifie their furie but theyr De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: How much more, ſhall this King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, whoſe wrath is ſo kindled for theyr wickedneſſe, condemne them into ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Darkneſſe, where ſhall bee wayling and gnaſhing of teeth, (for no dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion ſo lothſomly ſtinketh in the noſtrils of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, as doth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, abhominable unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant man, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18516:29"/>of God;) yet not conſidering this, they goe on in a careleſſe ſecurity, heaping one ſinne upon another, till the burthen become unſupportable, and the vials of Gods wrath ready to bee powred on them, not once calling them, to theyr remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; or if they doe, it is ſo farre from Contrition, that it is rather a delight to them, often glorying in the often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittings ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; they neyther thinking of theyr account, nor their end, wherein yet they might haue ſome happines; if death were the diſſolving both of their body &amp; ſoule.</p>
               <p>For being rid of their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18516:29"/>bodies, they ſhould alſo be rid of theyr Soules and Sinnes; But foraſmuch, as it is evident, that the Soule is immortall, there is left no comfort for the wicked to truſt in. Therfore, let ſuch remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ESAV, Who hauing once rejected the Bleſſing,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> could not after obtayne it, though he ſought it with teares; when it is too late, with the fiue Fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, they may cry; Lord,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>25</hi>
                  </note> Lord, open to vs; but the gates of Mercy will bee ſhut, and it will be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>I know you not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then woe bee to the ſinfull wicked men, that haue not power to turne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18516:30"/>from the filthy workes of this finfull and wretched World, that hindereth them from the bliſsfull ſtate, and keepeth backe theyr Soules from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God: For when Gods Serjeant Death, ſhall arreſt them, and they ſhall bee ſummon'd to appeare before the Tribunall of the Almighty, with what terrible feare will that Soule be ſhaken and ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with how many ſpeares of a piercing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is hee gored and thruſt through; he will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin to thinke of the time paſt, preſent, and that to come; the time paſt, he may behold with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18516:30"/>to perceiue how faſt it fleeted, and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſinnes therein committed, the which were accounted pleaſures, but are now terrors, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of which, he muſt anſwere; for as ſaith a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher: An accuſing Conſcience is the ſecret, &amp; moſt terrible thing that can bee, at the approaching and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Death, and infinit &amp; vnſpeakable are the feares and griefes it will bring with it; for then hee will grieve, that the time of Repentance hath beene ſo ill &amp; lewdly paſt, he ſeeth the divine Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements which he hath contemned: he is aflicted,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18516:31"/>becauſe he ſeeth the inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table houre approach, of rendring an account, &amp; of the divine juſt vengance; he would tarry ſtill, but he is conſtrained to depart; he would recover that is paſt, but time is not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? if he looke behind him, he ſeeth the courſe and race of his whole life led, as a moment of time; if he looke before, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth the infinit ſpace of Eternity which expecteth him, he ſorroweth and ſobbeth, becauſe he hath loſt the joy of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Eternity, which hee might haue obtained in ſo ſhort a time; hee tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe, becauſe he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18516:31"/>hath loſt the ineffable ſweetneſſe of perpetuall delight, for one ſenſuall, carnall, and momentany pleaſure; he bluſheth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that for that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which is Wormes-meat, he hath diſpiſed that which Angels prize ſo highly; and weighing the glory of thoſe immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall riches, hee is confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he hath changed them for the baſeneſſe and vildeneſſe of Temporall things; but when he caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his eyes upon things below, and ſeeth the darke and obſcure valley of this world, and beholdeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it, the ſhining bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of eternall Light,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18516:32"/>then he confeſſeth, that all that he loved in this world, was blacke night and ugly darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>To behold the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is as ill; for there hee can finde nothing but weakeneſſe and paines; his friends eyther mourning by him, or elſe not able to ſtay with him, to ſee his torments, which in this life, God hath begun to let him taſte; having painefull Limbes, darke Eyes, a faultering Tongue, hard browes, ſhort breath, and a panting heart, haſting to appeare before God, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he muſt behold; not as his Father, but a moſt feirce Iudge, whoſe pure eyes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18516:32"/>beheld all his actions, and that through all his life ſaw nothing but wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no ſorrowing teares to waſh away thoſe pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and therefore that leporous life muſt receiue a heauie condemnation: there will not be any to ſpeake for him, neyther will he be able to anſwere one word for a thouſand; all thoſe pleaſures now ſtand up to accuſe him, and his owne Conſcience giues in evidence againſt him, ſaying to himſelfe the words of SALOMON;<note place="margin">Pro. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> How haue I hated inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, and I haue not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the voyce of my tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18516:33"/>nor enclined mine eare to them that inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me; woe is me poore wretch, into what a labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth haue my ſinnes led me, how ſuddenly, and thinking nothing leſſe, hath this houre intrapped me, how hath it ruſhed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, I never dreamed of it; what doe now my Honours profit me, what doe now all my Dignities helpe me, what doe all my friends for me, what profit doe now my ſervants bring mee, what fruit doe I now reape of all my rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and goods which I was wont to poſſeſſe; for now a ſmall piece of ground of ſeaven foot will containe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18516:33"/>me, and I muſt be content with a dwelling in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Coffin, and with a lodging in a poore Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſheet; my riches, ſhall remaine here behind mee, which I ſcraped together with ſo great toyle, and ſweating, others ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them, and ſhall ſpend them on theyr pleaſures, onely my ſinnes, which I haue committed in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, wayte upon me, that I may ſuffer deſerved puniſhment for them; what can I make now of all my Pleaſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, ſeeing they are all over-paſt, onely theyr dregges are my Potion, which are ſcruples and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18516:34"/>bytings of Conſcience, which like Thornes doe pierce me, and runne thorough my miſerable heart.</p>
               <p>In what taking is this poore Soule; if time were now againe, with what an auſtere kinde of life would hee paſſe it, how would hee ſhun all thoſe alluring Syrens, ſower ſauce findes he for his ſweetes, and for a minute of Pleaſures, muſt poſſeſſe a world of Woes; nay, woes without end, ſoone ended thoſe delights, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are thoſe miſeries.</p>
               <p>O thou wretched man! thou that didſt choſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſit by the Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18516:34"/>of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> then by induring a little weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome travailes, to enter into the promiſed Land, which floweth with Milk and Honey; See! O ſee now, what a long chayne of Miſeries, thoſe thy ſhort Pleaſures have wrought thee. O thou fooliſh and ſenceleſſe! hadſt thou no reſpect to the death of CHRIST, who dyed to redeeme thee, but that by thy ſinnes, thou muſt anew Crucifie him, and make his Wounds to bleed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh? Thou haſt againe, nayled him to the Croſſe by thy pollutions! thou haſt againe, pierc'd his ſide, not with one, but many
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18516:35"/>ſpeares of Blaſphemy, and as it were piece-meale, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him from Heaven! thou haſt grinded him, by thy oppreſſions, which thou didſt to maintaine thy ſuperfluous delights.</p>
               <p>It was his love, that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to undergoe his Fathers wrath, for thy ſake; but what one ſinne, haſt thou left for his? Canſt thou ſay, and that truly, that thou haſt ſpared one diſh from thy Belly, to feed his hungry Members; or one Garment from thy exceſſive apparell, to cloth the naked; or one houres ſleepe, to meditate on his miſeries: a poore requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of ſuch infinite Love!
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18516:35"/>Was CHRIST ſtretched on the Croſſe, and couldeſt thou recount it nothing to ſtretch thy ſelfe vpon thy downy Beds of ſinne? Did CHRIST ſuck downe Vineger and Gall for thee, and couldeſt thou without pricke of Conſcience, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit with overflowne Boles? Was CHRIST crowned with Thornes, and couldeſt thou crowne thy ſelfe with eaſe and pleaſure? Then now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, (O thou rich Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton!) thou, who wouldeſt never caſt up thine eyes to behold the true happines, till it was too late, and conſider what the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Fleſh now
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18516:36"/>profit you, which you then ſo much delighted in? What is become of your Riches? where are your Honours? where are your Treaſures? where are your Delights? were are your Ioyes; the ſeaven yeares of Plenty are paſt, and other ſeaven yeares of Dearth and ſcarcity are come, which have devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up all your Plenty, no memory or footſteps being left of it.<note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> As it is in IOB, Drought and heate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Snow waters; ſo doth the Grave, thoſe that have Sinned; your Glory is now periſhed, and your Felicity is drowned in the ſea of Sorrowes, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18516:36"/>your delights have not profited you, which you injoyed in this World; but they ſhall bee the cauſes of greater Torments: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Glutton in the Goſpell, who fared delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly every day, being in Hell; was not that mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Tongue, moſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, which gave him the greateſt delight in Sin.</p>
               <p>Nay, ſpeedily and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, this horror ruſheth upon them; for, as everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Felicity, doth quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow the Godly, in the ſhort race of theyr Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; ſo everlaſting Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, quickly followeth the ungodly, in the ſhort race of theyr worldly Felicity.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:18516:37"/>
               <p> It were better therefore, for a man to live poorely, being aſſured of the bliſte of Heaven, then to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived thereof, though during life hee poſſeſſe all worldly riches; for intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, are the burthens they bring with them, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Scripture ſayth; Where much is given, much is againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: beſides, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the ungodly ſhall periſh, as ſaith IOB; The pitifull man,<note place="margin">Ioh, <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall forget him, the Worme ſhall feele his ſweetneſse, he ſhall bee no more remembred, and the Wicked ſhall bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken like a Tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18516:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Motives and Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to true Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
               <p>HAving already ſpoken of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtability of Mans life, &amp; the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched eſtate the Wicked is in, at the houre of his Death; I will now alſo ſet downe, ſome Motives for incouragements to true Godlineſse, wherin it ſhall eaſily bee diſcerned, that Godlineſse excelleth Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſse, as farre as Light excelleth Darkneſse; It is a thing, both uſuall and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18516:38"/>to ſee how men goe on in wickedneſse, and can neyther bee drawne, to thinke of theyr end by the dayly examples of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; nor wonne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, the infinitneſse of Gods Love by their dayly preſervations; they call not once to theyr remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, the ſaying of the Apoſtle PAVL, wherein hee admoniſheth them, to worke out theyr Salvation with feare and trembling; by which, hee depriveth them of all kind of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and the Prophet IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REMIAH cryeth unto them and ſayth;<note place="margin">Jerem. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> O earth! earth! earth! heare the Word of the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18516:38"/>
               <p> Shewing thereby, that howſoever they eſteeme of themſelves, yet, they are but duſt; whoſe glory is but for a moment, and all theyr Pleaſures, but <hi>Decep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio viſus;</hi> For that there is no Peace (ſaith the Lord) of the Wicked.<note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, conſider this yee that forget GOD, leaſt he teare you in pieces, and there bee none to deliver you; feare this God, for he is iuſt; love this God,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> for hee is Mercifull; ſtand in awe and Sinne not, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with your hearts, conſider your wayes, make your Peace with him, ſeeke the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> whileſt he may bee found; If his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18516:39"/>wrath be kindled, yea but a little, bleſſed are all thoſe that puts theyr truſt in him.</p>
               <p>O taſte, and ſee! how good GOD is, he is a God of Mercies, and delights not in the Death of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as hee ſayth; Have I any pleaſure at all,<note place="margin">Ezech. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> that the Wicked ſhould dye, ſayth the Lord; and not that hee ſhould returne from his wayes and live: hee will bee found of them that ſeeke him, hee hath inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his word for it, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith; Thoſe that come to mee, I will not caſt away; nay, hee calleth with aboundance of love: Come unto mee,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> all yee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18516:39"/>that are wearie and heavie laden with the burthen of your ſinnes, and I will eaſe you; hee is that good Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritaine, he may powre in Wine to make thoſe wounds of your Sinnes to ſmart, but hee will againe refreſh you with the oyle of his Mercies: O then! proſtrate thy ſelfe at his feete, creepe under the wing of his compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for he is ſlow to wrath,<note place="margin">Ioel. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and of much mercy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth him of the euill: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! it was thy weakeneſſe that made thee ſinfull, and thy ſins haue made the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, &amp; thy miſerie muſt now ſue to his mercie; if thy miſery were without
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18516:40"/>ſinne, then thou mighteſt pleade before his Iuſtice, and his Iuſtice would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thee; but for that it proceedeth from ſinne, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the barre of his mercy, and thou ſhalt finde the luſtre thereof to ſhine through all his workes; remember Chriſts owne words were:<note place="margin">Math. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of <hi>Jſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> what, though with the woman in the Goſpell, he call thee dogge, wilt thou therefore leaue off thy ſute; conſider, that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mother many times for faults committed by her childe, hideth her louing countenance and as it were
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18516:40"/>altogether reiecteth it, not for any hatred ſhe beareth to the childe, but thereby to indere the obtaining of his favour, and to cauſe the greater feare of offending; if then, thou ſeaſing thy ſute goeth without mercy, whome wilt thou accuſe: Chriſt ſayd to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Thy deſtruction is of thy ſelfe, O <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> but in me, is thy ſaluation. Chriſt came not, to call the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>Hee is infinitely good, and hurteth no man, vnleſſe the blame be in himſelfe, through his owne default; for, as the Sunne beame, is cleare and comfortable in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18516:41"/>it ſelf, and ſo is it to the eye that is ſound, yet to a ſore eye, it is very grieuous, not through any default in the ſunne, but by the diſeaſed diſpoſition of the eye; ſo albeit, he in himſelfe, be perfectly good, and doth nothing but good; yet to an vnrepentant ſinner he is grievous and terrible, but if he returne to him by unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance, he ſoone inclineth to mercy; as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident in that wo man, whom Chriſt ſo called; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her humiliation and acknowledging her ſelfe to be no better, ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this gracious anſwer; Be it vnto the euen as thou wilt; and againe, in the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites;</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18516:41"/>though his decree was gone out againſt them, that yet forty dayes, and <hi>Ninivie</hi> ſhould be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Ionah. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> upon their unfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, he alſo repented of that euill, and with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of mercy revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that ſentence; For the eyes of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chro.</hi> 16</note> beholds all the earth, to ſtrengthen them, that with a perfect heart beleeve, and hope in him; and againe, it is ſayd; O how good is the Lord unto them,<note place="margin">Lament. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> that put theyr truſt in him, and to the Soule that ſeeketh after him; never was there any forſaken, that put theyr truſt in him: and though the hand of your Faith, be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18516:42"/>not ſtrong enough to lay faſt hold on him, as IA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COB did, who ſayd; I will not let thee goe, unleſſe thou bleſſe mee;<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> yet, if hee perceiue thee creeping af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, hee will imbrace thee, for hee hath ſayd; The bruiſed Reede,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> I will not breake, and the ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Flaxe, I will not quench; that is, hee will not reiect the deſires of the heart, though in weake meaſure, if unfeyned, and what he hath promiſed, is Truth.</p>
               <p>Hee loveth not, as man loveth; for they in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will regard vs, but if Afflictions or wants come, they regard us not; but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18516:42"/>ſo farre is our good God from this, that his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sonne CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, tooke our ſhape up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, ſuffering Hunger, Cold, Nakedneſſe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and Scornings; for his owne mouth teſtified, That the Foxes had Holes, and the Birds of the Ayre had Neſts, but the Sonne of Man, had not whereon to lay his head; ſhowing thereby to us, how farre hee was from contemning our Povertie, or refuſing us for our wants; let us therefore, flie to this God, who will not fayle us nor forſake us: let us caſt our care upon him, for hee careth for us, and ſet us firſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18516:43"/>ſeek the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the righteouſneſse thereof, and all things elſe ſhall bee miniſtred unto us.</p>
               <p>How many haue beene knowne, which have gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to themſelves, Riches, or Honours, by unlawfull meanes, that have proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but if for a time they have ſeemed to doe well, their Poſteritie have come to ruine, and theyr owne ill-gathered treaſure, like a dilating Gangrene, hath rotted theyr owne memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and conſumed every part of theyr heyres poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; ſeeming as it were, a Curſe and doome, intay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the land upon the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18516:43"/>ſucceſsour, and ſo proveth, not a Bleſſing, but the bane of him that Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
               <p>They may for a time, flouriſh like a Bay Tree, but ſuddainely they fade and their place is no where to bee found. Oh therefore! that they would conſider, what great evils, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inconveniences, this ſmall proſperity bringeth with it, they ſhould find this love of Riches, more to afflict, by deſire, then to delight, by uſe: for it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrappeth the Soule, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; bindeth it in infinit cares, it allureth it with ſundry delights,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18516:44"/>provoketh it to ſinne, and diſturbeth the quiet, no leſſe of the body then of the Soule, and that which is greater; Riches are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gotten, without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, nor poſſeſsed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out care, nor loſt, without griefe; but that which is worſt, they are ſeldome gathered, without ſinne and offence to GOD? Why then, ſhould man bee ſo greedy of this Worlds pelfe, life beeing ſo ſhort, and death following at our heeles? What neede is there of ſo great Proviſion, for ſo ſhort a Iourney? What would man doe with ſo great Riches; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, ſeeing that the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18516:44"/>leſſe he hath, the more lightly and freely hee may walke, and when hee ſhall come to the end of his Pilgrimage, if he be poore, his eſtate ſhall not be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then rich mens, who are loden with much gold; the Grave ſhall both alike containe them, as ſayth IOB;<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> The ſmall and great are there, and the Servant is free from his Maſter.</p>
               <p>Nay, it is better with the poore, then with the rich; for they ſhall feele leſſe griefe in parting with this traſh and pelfe of the World, and a ſmaller ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt is to be rendred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD; whereas on the other ſide, Rich men
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18516:45"/>leaves theyr Mountaines of Gold, with great griefe of heart, which they adored as GOD; neyther are they, without exceeding gerat hazard and danger, in rendring an accompt for them: Beſides, as hee came forth of his Mothers Wombe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> ſo naked ſhall he returne, to goe as hee came; and ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his labour which he may carry away in his hand.<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore a little that a Righteous man hath, is better then the Riches of many wicked. I have ſeene ſayth DAVID, in the ſame Pſalme; The wicked in great power, and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe like a greene
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18516:45"/>Bay tree, yet hee paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and loe hee was not; I ſought him but hee could not bee found, the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours ſhall be deſtroyed together, the end of the Wicked ſhall bee cut off; but marke the upright man, and behold the Iuſt, for the end of that man is Peace.</p>
               <p>Thrice bleſſed then is that man, that feareth God, and they whoſe God the Lord is, and he that ſots his feare alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes;<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> For they ſhall bee delivered out of ſixe troubles, and in the ſeaventh, no evils ſhall touch them, in Famine, he ſhall redeeme them from
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18516:46"/>Death, and in Warre, from the power of the ſword, they ſhall come to the Grave in a full age, like as a ſhocke of Corne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in, in his ſeaſon: They may for a time bee bungry, but they ſhall be filld, for God himſelfe will feed them with bleſſings from aboue and from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath. Even naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will not ſuffer them to doubt, for he that giveth meate in due ſeaſon, to Ants and Wormes of the Earth, will he ſuffer Man to famiſh, who night and day, ſerve and obey him, as CHRIST himſelfe ſaith in MATTHEVV;<note place="margin">Math. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Behold the Fowles of the heaven,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18516:46"/>for they ſow not, neyther reape nor cary into Barnes, yet your heavenly Father feedeth them, are yee not much better then they; This happines moved DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID to invite us to ſerve the Lord, ſaying; O feare the Lord! yee that be his Saints,<note place="margin">Pſalm <hi>34</hi>
                  </note> for they that feare the Lord lack nothing, the Lyons doe lacke and ſuffer hunger, but they that feeke the Lord, ſhall want no manner of thing that is good.</p>
               <p>The ungodly man, when he is full of wealth dyeth for hunger, and when they ſit even up to the lips in water, yet they are ſlaine with thirſt, as the Poets
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18516:47"/>in times paſt, fabled of TANTALVS. But though many and great be the troubles of the Righteous, yet the Lord delivereth them out of all. For the eyes of the Lord is over the Righteous, and his Eare is open to theyr cry, but the Face of the Lord is againſt them that do evill,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 3 4</note> to cut off theyr Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance from the Eatth.</p>
               <p>Who would be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling then, to ſuffer ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and ſcornings, rather then with the wicked, to injoy the pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon;<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> God himſelfe will wipe all teares from theyr eyes, hee will give them Ioyes for theyr Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18516:47"/>as hee ſayth; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are yee that now Weepe, for yee ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, troubles in this life, are badges of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Whom the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth,<note place="margin">Prov. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> hee chaſtiſeth, and correcteth every Sonne that he chuſeth with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;<note place="margin">Luke, <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore, poſſeſſe your Soules,<note place="margin">Iohn, <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber who it is, that ſayd; You are not of the World, as I am not of the World, the world hateth you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hated mee firſt, if you were of the world, the world would love you.</p>
               <p>Oh, bleſſed Sufferings! that makes us like to God himſelfe, if wee had the Wiſedome of SALOMON,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18516:48"/>the Treaſure of CRoeSVS, and the long life of ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THVSALEM, and out of the favour and love of God, our Wiſedome were Fooliſhneſſe, for to know him, is perfect wiſedome, our Riches were droſſe; for riches will not avayle in the day of Wrath, and that life, ſo long and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly led, no better, then a man that dreames hee is a King, honoured of all and wanting nothing, when waking, hee findes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hated of all, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:18516:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Of the Peace of a good Conſcience, and the Ioyfull end of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</head>
               <p>SALOMON, having ſet himſelfe to behold all things that were under the Sun, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken to himſelfe, all that could bee delightfull, for what can he doe more that commeth after the King, at laſt concludeth;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> That all the dayes of Man, are ſorrowes, and his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, griefe; therefore ſayth he; I hated life, for all is Vanity and vexation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18516:49"/>of Spirit; and perceiving how apt men were, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low what delights this world could affoord them, ſcoffes at theyr folly, and by way of deriſion ſayth: Rejoyce O young man in thy Youth,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> &amp; let thy heart cheare thee in the dayes of thy youth, and walke in the wayes of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes, yet would hee not let them goe on thus, but gives them an <hi>Jtem,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; But know, that for all theſe things, God will bring thee to Iudgement, for though, ſayth hee: A Sinner doe evill an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times, and his dayes bee prolonged; yet ſurely
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18516:49"/>I know, that it ſhal be well with them, that feare God.</p>
               <p>Theſe Caveats, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man placeth before his remembrance, leaſt hee ſhould fall into errors, and making his life of no value to him, hee deſpiſeth all things, onely ayming at that, may make him hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, which is, a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for that will bring him peace at the laſt; death being to a godly man, the ending of Sorrowes, and the beginning of Ioyes; he doth then begin to live with God, when hee dyes to the World,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> as it is ſayd in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes;</hi> Who ſo feareth the Lord, it ſhall goe well with him at the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18516:50"/>laſt, and in the day of his Death, hee ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>And St. IOHN, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to Write: Bleſſed are the Dead,<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> that dye in the Lord, even ſo ſayth the Spirit; that they may reſt from theyr labours, &amp; their works follow them. How can that man bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that heareth this of the Lord, in the houre of his Death, when he findeth himſelfe haſting thither, where hee ſhall receive that, which he hath all his life-time deſired.</p>
               <p>And Saint AVGVSTINS, ſpeaking of the Death of a Good man, ſayth; He that deſireth to bee diſſolved, &amp; be with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> dyeth not Patiently, but liveth Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18516:50"/>and dyeth delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, and it may be ſayd; That like a Swan, he dyeth ſinging, yeilding the glory to God which calleth him. With what joy, doth that Soule behold his end, who hath all his Life-time poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed a good Conſcience, nothing fearefull, can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelfe before him, he ſees all his ſinnes, not of a Crimſon die, but White as wooll, waſhed by the blood of Chriſt; he beholds him, not as his Iudge, but his Sauiour and Mediatour, his Iudge is, his Brother, God in Chriſt is become his Father, hee hath no debts to pay, <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> on the Croſſe hath Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18516:51"/>the hand writing that was againſt him, and hath not onely made him free, but alſo an heyre of the Kingdome of Heaven. The preſence of Death, is not terrible to him, for he feareth not Death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee feared GOD, and hee that feareth him need feare none other: hee feareth not Death, becauſe he feared Life, but feare of Death, are the effects of an evill Life; hee feareth not Death, becauſe through all his life hee learned to dye, and prepared himſelfe to dye; but a man prepared and provident, need not feare his Enemy; he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not Death, becauſe ſo
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18516:51"/>long as he lived, he ſought for thoſe things that might helpe him, that is, for Vertues and good Workes; hee feareth not Death, becauſe to a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, Death is not death, but a ſleepe, it is not Death, but an end of all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, it is not Death but away unto life, and a Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto Paradice; for hee knoweth, that Death; hath loſt all the bitterneſſe of Death, after it hath paſſed through the veynes of Life, and that it hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſweetneſſe of life: hee feareth not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Divels, becauſe he hath CHRIST his defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Captaine: he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18516:52"/>not the horror of the grave, becauſe he knoweth that his body is ſowne a corrup tible body, but ſhall riſe againe, in incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body, often boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the ſtrength hee hath gained by <hi>Christ,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with cheerefulneſſe of ſpirit; O Death, where is thy ſting?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> O Grave, where is thy victory? The ſtrong man, death comes not upon him una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares; for hee hath layd up in ſtore for himſelfe a good foundation againſt this time,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note> which was to come, that hee might lay hold on Eternall life.</p>
               <p>Even the breſt-plate of righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> the ſhield
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18516:52"/>of Faith, the Helmet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spirit, having his loynes girt about with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and his feete ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of Peace, what hope now hath his enemy of any advantage, though helped by the weakeneſſe of his owne fleſh: Death was ever expected, and therefore provided for: he alwayes lived as in the preſence of GOD, having a ſtrict eye over all his actions, and though now Satan bend all his Forces againſt him, becauſe hee hath but a ſmall time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſiege muſt bee ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and therefore preſents
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18516:53"/>that before him which he deareſt loued, his Wife, Children, Father, and Friends, with his whole Eſtate, Honour, Riches, Youth, Health, Strength, and Life it ſelfe, thereby thinking to ſhake his hold; for this ſubtill ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my knoweth, they are not loſt without griefe, which are poſſeſsed with Love; yet fayles he of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for it is certaine, hee that in this life knoweth of feweſt delights, leaſt of all other, feareth Death, ſo he having never prized them otherwayes then they were in themſelves, parteth from them with the leſſe trouble, yet weake
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18516:53"/>nature ſtrugling with him, may a little dazle him, but calling to minde the Words of his Saviour, who ſayth:<note place="margin">Mark. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> He that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Father, Mother, Wife, Children, houſe and lands, for my ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, hee gaines ſtrength, and with the greater joy his Soule anſwers? Oh ſweet IESVS I ſhall I not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgoe all theſe, who for my ſake, ſuffered the Viols of thy Fathers wrath due to me for ſinne, to be powred out upon thee, and in thy body indured that, which I deſerved? It was for my ſake, thou waſt borne in a Stable, and layd
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18516:54"/>in a Cratch; for me, thou flying into Egypt, livedſt ſeaven yeares in baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for me, thou didſt faſt, thou didſt watch, thou didſt run hither &amp; thither, thou didſt ſweate Water and Bloud, thou didſt Weepe, and thou didſt prove by experience, thoſe miſeries which my ſinnes deſerved; and yet thou waſt without ſinne, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there guile found in thy mouth, neyther hadſt thou offended, but waſt offended; for me, thou waſt taken, forſaken of thine, denyed, ſold, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with fiſts, ſpet upon, mocked, whipped, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Thornes, reviled
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18516:54"/>with blaſphemies, hanged upon the Croſſe, Dead, and Buried, thou wert not onely forſaken of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall things, but alſo of the Divine comfort, as thy owne Mouth teſtified, when thou cryedſt out, <hi>My God, my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>why baſt thou forſaken mee;</hi> Oh the height of Loved Oh the depth of unmeaſurable humility! Oh the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Mercy! Oh the bottomleſſe Pit of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Goodnes: Oh Lord! if I be ſo greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to thee, becauſe thou haſt redeemed mee, what doe I not owe thee, for the manner by which thou haſt redeemed mee:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18516:55"/>thou haſt redeemed mee with moſt great dolours! with contumelies, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominies, not to be borne; inſomuch, that thou waſt made a reproach of men, and the ſcorne of the whole world; through thy reproaches, thou haſt honoured me; through thy accuſations, thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended me; through thy bloud, thou haſt waſhed me; through thy death, thou haſt rayſed me; and through thy teares, thou haſt freed me, from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting weeping and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth: thine were the Wounds, that healed my ſores: thine was the backe, that bare
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18516:55"/>my ſorrowes; thine was the prize, that quit my ſcores: thou aſſumedſt my fleſh, to redeeme me here, and thou raigneſt as King, to crowne me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Thus by thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Torments, thou didſt free me from all evill; and ſhall I be unwilling to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the deprivation of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle happineſſe, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during of a few paines to come unto thee, who haſt thus dearely purchaſed me for thy ſelfe: theſe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſo raviſhed his ſoule, that with aint PAVL he thinkes himſelfe in the third Heaven, hee hath drunke ſo freely of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Paradice, one drop
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18516:56"/>of which is greater then the Ocean, which alone is able to quench the thirſt of the whole World, that he loatheth theſe puddell Waters, accounting all things but droſſe and dung in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all is to him in compariſon, no more then the light of a Candle, is to the glorious beames of the Sunne, he is now ſo farre from eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming eyther them, or life, that he deſires to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and be with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he longs for the day of his diſſolution, life being to him a Priſon, and with often groanes and ſighes, cryoth, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly;</hi> and with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18516:56"/>DAVID hee ſayth: O how I long to appeare before GOD. If life were offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, with all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof, hee would deſpiſe it, for hee is fitted for God, he is no man for the World, his Soule hath too exactly looked into the worth of it, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with all the glithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhewes thereof, the which hee findes to bee vayne and fleeting, and nothing permanent in this Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:18516:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IIII.</hi> Of the deferring of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous it is, and of the deceiveableneſſe of worldly Pleaſures.</head>
               <p>HAving now ſeen the quiet Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Bleſſedneſse of the Godly, at the houre of his Death, mee thinkes it ſhould incourage every man to prepare himſelfe for his end in the time of Proſperity, leaſt when the time of changing ſhall come, they bee found na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and bare, and ſo lye
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18516:57"/>open to all the aſſaults and batteries of Sathan, many there, bee to whom the Day of Iudgement ſeemes terrible, not remembring the day of theyr Death, which is the firſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the which whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver paſſeth, on ſuch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhall have no power; as Saint IOHN ſayth in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> The defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Repentance proves dangerous. Yet ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious man will ſay; When I am come to old Age, I will runne to the remedy of Repentance: Dare mans frailtie preſume thus much of himſelfe, ſeeing hee hath not one day of all his Life, in his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18516:58"/>owne power, for though God hath promiſed Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to the Penitent; yet he hath not promiſed to morrow to a ſinner: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whilſt it is called to day,<note place="margin">Hebr. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> heare his voyce and hearden not your hearts, leaſt you enter into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Follow the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of that Kingly Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, make no tarrying to turne unto the Lord;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and put not off from day to day, for ſoda nly ſhall his wrath come, and in the time of vengeance he ſhall deſtroy thee: beſides, there is another evill; ſinne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no reſtraint, but free liberty, to runne on in his owne current; how
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18516:58"/>dangerous doth it proove, and how hard is it to ſtop the courſe thereof, being once growne to a cuſtome: Is it not uſually knowne, that hee that driveth a Nayle into a Poſt, faſteneth it at the firſt ſtroke that he giveth it, but more firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the ſecond ſtroke, but ſo faſt at the third, that it can hardly bee pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out againe; and the oftner he ſtriketh it, the faſter it ſticketh, and is pulled out againe, with the greater difficulty: So in every one of mans wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked actions, vice is driuen deepely into their ſoules, as if it were with a Mallet, and there it ſticketh ſo
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18516:59"/>faſt, that it can by no meanes be pulled foorth, but by the bitter teares of Repentance, which are ſeldome and very hardly found; this ſame thing our Saviour ſhewed in the rayſing of LAZARVS, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foure dayes dead; whom he called foorth,<note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> with groaning of ſpirit: whereas he rayſed others that were dead, with farre eaſier tokens of difficulty; ſignifying to us thereby, how great a myracle it is, that God ſhould convert one buried in the cuſtome of ſinning; yet, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering theſe things, how doth time paſſe on, and what numberleſſe ſinnes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18516:59"/>are committed without feare to offend, or care to provoke him to anger; through whoſe Gates thou muſt enter, before whoſe feet thou muſt lye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, will thou nill thou; whoſe mercy thou muſt ſue and deplore; Thou art piunged in the Gulfe of ſinne, he onely muſt rayſe theee? thou art wounded, he onely can healt thee? thou art ſicke to the death, hee onely can give thee life? Oh then, feare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him! of whoſe helpe thou ſtandeſt in need every moment,<note place="margin">Iſa. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> tremble to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to anger, who hath for unrepentant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, prepared a deepe and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18516:60"/>large pit, the Piller there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord, like a ſtreame of brimſtone doth kindle it; beware of going on in delights, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remembring your end, leſt you be like the Fiſhes, that ſports themſelves ſo long in the delightſome ſtreames of the River <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan;</hi> that unawares they plunge themſelves in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re mertuum,</hi> from whence there is no Redemption; many are the baytes and ſnares, which are layd for man in this life, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red over with glittering wealth, and delightſome Pleaſures, but bare theſe deceits, and cauſe them to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18516:60"/>appeare in their own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thou ſhalt finde this World to bee a Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of ſorrowes and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, a Schoole of Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a laborinth of Errors, a dungeon of Darkneſſe, a Market-place of Couſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, a way beſet with Theeves, a ditch full of mud, and a Sea continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toſt and troubled with ſtormes and Tempeſts: what other thing is the world, but a barren Land, a field full of Thiſtles and Weeds, a Wood full of Thornes, a flouriſhing Garden, but bringing forth no fruit, a River of Teares, a Fountaine of Cares, a ſweet poyſon; A Tragedy
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18516:61"/>pleaſantly framed, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull Phrenzie; the Worlds reſt hath labour, the Security of it without ground, the feare of it is without cauſe, the Labour of it without fruit, the Teares without purpoſe, and the purpoſes without ſucceſſe, the Hope of it is vayne, the joy feyned, and the Sorrow true, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this World, is but the ſinging of Syrens, ſweet, but a deadly Potion, a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, artificially painted without, but within full of venemous poyſon: If the World fawne upon thee, it doth it that it may deceive thee; if it Exalt thee, it doth it that thy fall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18516:61"/>may bee the greater; if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee merry, it doth it that it afterwards with ſorrow may breake thy heart; it giveth all her goods with a mixture of incomparable heavineſſe and griefes, and that with the greateſt uſurie: if a Sonne bee borne to thee and ſoone after dye, thy ſorrow will be ſeaven fold greater then was thy Ioy, the thing loſt, more afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, then found joyeth; Sickneſſe more excrucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, then Health glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; Injury more tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, then Honour conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth; to conclude, what good things are found in the World, which are not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18516:62"/>counterfeit, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vill which are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deed; If theſe things he ſo indeed as they are, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould man deſire to ſtay any longer in this land of <hi>Aegypt</hi> to gather ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who would not flye out of this <hi>Babilon,</hi> who would not deſire to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from this fire of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore, that the World is beſet with ſo many ſnares, and that ſo many downfals and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckes are in the way, and the flame of Vices doe ſo burne us, who at any time can bee ſecure and ſafe, as the Wiſe man ſayth;<note place="margin">Prov. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Can a man take fire in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18516:62"/>and his cloathes not be burnt, or can a man goe upon Coales,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> and his feet not burnt; he that toucheth Pitch, ſhall be defiled with the ſame; eſtrange then thy minde from theſe ycie Vanities; liſten and thou ſhalt heare CHRIST, who ſeeth the danger thou art falling into, calling unto thee, that hee may teach thee a way to prevent thy hurt, and ſaying; Behold, I ſtand at the doore and knocke, runne and open to this Phyſitian of thy Soule. O refuſe him not, neyther delay his entrance, for thou art ſicke, and he will give thee to drinke of the water of Life, neyther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18516:63"/>for money, nor by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but freely, and taking thy fill, without limitation, and freely too, being of his owne Grace and Mercy.</p>
               <p>Can you then, knowing to whom you are to open; ſtand with delayes; as I cannot yet, I will anon, but this I cannot yet, I will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non; is deferred ſo long, that this heavenly gheſt goeth away without a Lodging, by reaſon of which, he will hardly bee brought againe, without many teares: Oh then I be ready at the firſt knock to open; I meane the firſt good motion, ſo ſhall you receive a gheſt, whoſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18516:63"/>company is ſweeter, then the honey and the honey Combe; On heart! more hard then ſtone, that can refuſe him; if conſidered who it is, it is CHRIST, the well-beloved Sonne of his Father, it is hee, in whom, God the Father is ſo well pleaſed, that all thy ſinnes are forgiven, being covered with the robe of his Righteouſneſſe; it is he, that ſuffered Rebukes, Buffetings, Scornings, Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings on, and at the laſt, death; I, and that, the moſt curſedſt death, even the death of the Croſſe, as it is written: Curſed are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that hang on a Tree.<note place="margin">Galat. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things being ſo,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18516:64"/>have you not hearts harder then an Adamant, thus to oppoſe his entrance: Oh doe not deferre this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to the time to come, for one minute of this time (which now vainely ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from thee) is more precious, then the Treaſure of the whole world.</p>
               <p>Be like unto a wiſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> that having found a precious Pearle, goes and ſels all he hath to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it; what thing more precious then the Sonne of God, which heere offereth himſelfe unto thee? why art thou ſo ſlacke in giving him entertainement, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou him not worthy, becauſe thou beholdeſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18516:64"/>him in his Humility, poore and deſpiſed, or doth thy fleſh puffe thee up with a conceit beyond thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, if it doe, caſt thy eyes upon thy ſelfe, and conſider what thou waſt before thou waſt borne, what thou art now, being borne, and what thou ſhalt bee after Death: before thou waſt borne, thou waſt filthy and obſceane mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not worthy to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; now thou art dung, covered over with ſnow, and a while after thou ſhalt be meat for Wormes: why then, ſhouldeſt thou bee proud, ſeeing thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity is ſinne, thy Life mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and thy End putrifac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18516:65"/>and corruption.</p>
               <p>Having conſidered thus with thy ſelfe, tell mee if thou haſt not the greater reaſon to open with the more celerity,<note place="margin">Semel.</note> hee of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being willing to paſſe by theſe thy Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, wouldeſt thou not account that man moſt heatheniſh, who having a Friend, that had indured ſeaven yeares impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to keepe him from that bondage, &amp; at the laſt payed his Ranſome, at ſo deare a rate, as thereby his eſtate were for ever rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, otherwiſe hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to indure perpetuall Slavery: if this man, I ſay, ſhould come and knocke
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18516:65"/>at the doore of his Friend deſiring admittance, and acquainting him, with who it was, and hee for this his love, ſhould ſeeme not to know him, but bid him be gone and barre the doore againſt him; I know thou wouldeſt account him moſt inhumane and ungratefull,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5 3.</note> and yet how farre ſhort comes this of CHRIST'S love and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to thee, for the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement of thy Peace, was layd upon him, and with his ſtripes thou waſt healed.</p>
               <p>O wretched Soule! to looſe ſuch a Friend, Oh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie man! by this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, to deprive thy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18516:66"/>ſelfe of all Happines: for what greater Happineſſe canſt thou have, then to injoy that Fatherly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence by which God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth his, what ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Delights, then the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, the Light of wiſedome, the conſolations of the holy Ghoſt, the Ioy and Peace of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the good event of Hope, the true liberty of the Soule, the inward peace of the Heart, to bee heard in Prayer, to be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Tribulations, to be provided for temporall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and to bee ayded and to taſte of Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Comforts in death: whilſt I ſeriouſly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18516:66"/>upon theſe things, my Soule is as in a Rapture, me thinkes I ſee CHRIST IESVS comming in the Clouds, with thouſand of Angels about him, the Heavens and Earth flying away at his preſence, mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of damned Soules, yelling and crying to the Rocks and Mountaines, to fall upon them, and to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, from the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſight; The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels quaking and trembling expecting the denouncing of their Torments; and the Ioyes the Godly have at that houre: For as it is a day of horror and terror to the Wicked, ſo is it a day of joy and gladneſſe to the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18516:67"/>godly; for as the body of the one reſts in the earth, without taſte of thoſe miſeries it hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; even ſo the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, by this ſleepe of Death, is deprived of this bleſſedneſſe in their body, untill corruption hath put on incorruption, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality hath put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; and that they are wakened by the ſound of the Trumpet; which ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore CHRIST; when then their ſoules become againe reunited to their bodyes, and both with Ioy, beholds the face of God, not as their Iudge, for he is their Brother; and therefore
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18516:67"/>can expect from him, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but mercy; he hath purchaſed them for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with no meaner a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> price, then his owne precious bloud; and there fore, muſt needs bee to him acceptable, this is theyr yeare of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> this is the Marriage of the Lambe, with him they enter,<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and he is theyr God, and they are his Sonnes; they now behold his face, and his Name is in theyr fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads; They now, receive the fulneſſe of theyr Ioy,<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> they now, poſſeſſe that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe theyr Soules thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted for; they now, injoy the reward of all theyr la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: this bleſſedneſſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18516:68"/>truly conſidered on, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foordeth more pleaſures then the tongue of Man can utter, or his Soule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning in the Priſon of his fleſh, is able to receive, without crying out with the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> I am ſicke of Love. It is no marvell, that the Church cryeth; Come Lord IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, come quickly: for in this his comming, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth all happineſſe. Here is the finall end of all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſinnes; it onely, prooveth the waters of <hi>Mara</hi> to the ungodly; it is terrible to none, but the unrepentant, even they who had their eyes ſealed from beholding any other
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18516:68"/>Happines, then what ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their pleaſures; They which tooke to them the Timbrell and the Harp, and rejoyced in the ſound of the Organs, they ſpend theyr dayes in wealth, and were of them that ſayd: Speake no more to us in the name of the Lord; they ſayd to God, depart from us, for wee deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes. What is the Almighty, that we ſhould ſerve him? and what profit ſhall wee haue, if we pray unto him? Now alas! but too late, they ſee theyr owne follyes; now without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, they behold theyr owne miſeries; no marvell,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18516:69"/>though the mentioning of the day of Iudgement, be terrible to ſuch a man; who by his wickedneſſe, deprives himſelfe of all thoſe Bleſſedneſſes; for ill will it prove, if the day of Death, be not alwayes in his remembrance; which is the firſt judgement, and wherein he muſt ſtand ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther convicted, or acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; eyther condemned for his bad workes, or juſtified for his good, whereof he can have little hope, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hee meet his Iudge in the way, and make his peace with him, whilſt he may be found; yet, there is time to furniſh thy lamp with Oyle, yet the Gates
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18516:69"/>of Mercy are not ſhut, yet thou mayeſt ſo cry, as thou mayeſt bee ſatisfied with this gracious anſwer; <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> Whereas, if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thy Repentance from time to time, putting farre from thee the evill day, if thou doe not expect the comming of thy Lord, but become drunken, and fall to ſmiting thy fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, if thou hide thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the Earth, which God in his goodneſſe hath beſtowed on thee to better uſes: Thy Lord will come when he is not looked for,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and in a time when thou art not aware of, and caſt thee into utter Darkneſse,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18516:70"/>where ſhall bee wayling and gnaſhing of Teeth, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thee a juſt hyre for thy careleſſe ſecurity: It is not thy pleaſures, that can deferre thy calamities; it is not the inlarging thy Barnes, that can reſiſt thy miſery; the greatneſse of Friends will not availe; thy Iudge is blinde to Bribery, and deafe to all but Iuſtice, if his wrath be not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before he come to give ſentence, it will then be too late to expect mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:18516:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Comforts for the weake Chriſtian; and to beware of Backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding.</head>
               <p>OVR moſt ſubtle malicious Enemy retayning ſtill the hatred hee bare our firſt Parents at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſeeketh to bring us into ever laſting Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo to gaine us to himſelfe by one meanes or other; to a man nouzeled in Sinne, hee uſeth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes, then the lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him ſtill the faſter
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18516:71"/>aſleepe in worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; the Miſer he perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſtill to covet Riches, thereby making his Gold his God; by which meanes hee filleth up the meaſure of Wrath againſt the day of Iudgement: the Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer hee draweth on more eaſily, by the delightſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſinne, telling him that ſtolne bread is ſweet,<note place="margin">Prov. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and hid waters pleaſant: the Proud man, hee hath hud-wincked, not to thinke of time, but to account all loft, but what is ſpent in decking and ſetting himſelfe foorth in the Divels Feathers: Thus all ſinnes he leſſens, that ſo he may cauſe man to defer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18516:71"/>his repentance till the laſt, then the which, there is nothing more dangerous: but when he meets a child in religion, who is glad to ſuck milke from the ſweet paps of Gods word, him he ſo to ſceth &amp; ſhaketh, with telling him of his owne unworthines, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Gods Iuſtice, that the poore Soule is ready to leave his hold and to fall into deſperation, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſcarce to looke up to Gods Mercy; but if his weaknes become ſtrength and he be rayſed by Faith, then hee ſtrives to cauſe him to become weary and backward in well doing,</p>
               <p>Therefore, thou O man I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18516:72"/>that wouldeſt doe the good thou doeſt not, but through the deceiveable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. of thy fleſh ſtandeth loytering, and with SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOMONS fluggard cryeth; Yet a little ſleepe, a little ſlumber; a wake and behold CHRIST comming in the Clouds. Stand up and gird thy ſelfe like a man, lift up thy eye of Faith and behold thy Saviour, whoſe merits plead for thee? See him dying for thee, and thereby paying thy debts? See thy Iudge a juſt one, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will not require that againe, which Chriſt hath already ſatisfied, hee hath beheld the thoughts of thine heart, and found thy
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18516:72"/>deſires, are to ſerve him concerning, the inward Man, and though thou didſt fall into ſinnes moſt offenſive to the eyes of his Divine Maieſty, yet hee knowes, that the evill thou didſt hate, that thou didſt: But it was a Law in thy Members that ledde thee captive to the Law of ſin:<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> then if as a Captive forc't, it was no longer thou, but ſinne that dwelled in thee.</p>
               <p>Let the remembrances of theſe Mercies, waken thy Soule from the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of Sinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member who hath ſayd: Awake,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> thou that ſleepeſt and ariſe from the Dead, and CHRIST ſhall give
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18516:73"/>thee light? Hee calleth thee? Hee biddeth thee awake, let not theſe ſweet calles, ſtrike thee dead,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> as his preſence did the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who became aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and were as dead men; but rather let that voyce bee of as great power to thee, as it was to LAZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RVS; not onely to rayſe thee from the ſleepe,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> but alſo from the death of Sin. And bee as ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this love as THOMAS was, who no ſooner tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his Saviour, but cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out:<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> My Lord, and my God: Neyther deceive thy ſelfe, with a ſoothing conceit of what is not in thee;<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> For, the Tree is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18516:73"/>knowne by the fruit; for men cannot gather Grapes of Thornes, nor Figs of Thiſtles: A good man, out of the good Treaſure of his Heart,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> bringeth forth good things, and an evill man, out of the evill Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heart, bringeth forth evill things; ſo that howſoever thou mayſt ſeeme to the World, yet as a ſhadow doth alwayes follow the body, ſo feare and deſperation will at all times, and in all places, wayte upon an evill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeience.</p>
               <p>Let not thy Faith be as a Houſe built upon the Sands, which will ſhake with every blaſt of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18516:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:18516:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:18516:75"/>or Afflictions, but found it upon the Rocke CHRIST IESVS; againſt which, whatſoever bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſhall returne with a greater repulſe to it ſelfe, as not being able to move it; and having once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned this perfection, take heed of recoyling, for CHRIST ſayth; He that layeth hand upon the Plough and looketh backe, is not meet for the Kingdome of Heaven.<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>What though the way to Heaven be narrow, and full of Difficulties? Wilt thou not therefore, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred, perſeuere? Who would wiſh or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to walke in a way
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18516:75"/>ſtrowed with Roſes, and planted with divers fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Flowers, if the aſſured end of it be death; and who would refuſe a rough and difficult path, that leadeth unto life; is it not commonly ſeene, that many men to attaine to Preferment, run into moſt apparent dangers, and hazard the loſſe of theyr life; (nay I know thou wouldeſt doe it thy ſelfe) and ſhall it bee trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and grievous to thee, to doe that for thy Soule, which thou refuſeth not to doe for thy Body? Shall it ſeeme a great thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, to ſuffer a little trouble heere, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18516:76"/>thou mayſt eſcape eternall torment? What would not the rich cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man buryed in Hell, willingly doe, if he might have licence to come into the World againe, that he might amend his errors? Is it meet that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe leſſe now, then he would doe; ſeeing, that if thou doſt perſever in thy wickedneſſe, the ſame tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments remaine for thee.</p>
               <p>He that runneth a Race leaveth not till hee come to the Gole; So run as you may obtaine: Remember LOTS Wife, who looking backe became a Piller of Salt; ſo take heed, leſt thou by looking backe upon the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18516:76"/>vanities of this life, forget the care of thy Soule, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee by God; &amp; ſo of his child, become not a Piller of Salt, but a child of Perdition; a man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving much riches, is ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vetous of more, and what wealth to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Soule? A thing ſo great in it ſelfe; that what gayneth hee, that getteth the whole world, and looſeth his Soule; even as great a purchaſe, as hee, who having with much Labour and great charge, obtayned a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lewell, ſtraight giueth it for a trifle.</p>
               <p>Nay, were it ſo, it were the leſſe, for that were but
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18516:77"/>the undoing of the body, this the loſſe of the Soule; that friends againe may rayſe, this is a loſſe irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable: Wherefore, thinke no paynes weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, no labours irkſome, nor any troubles grievous, to attaine true happineſſe; For our light afflictions,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> which is but for a moment, worketh for us a farre more exceeding &amp; eternall weight of Glory, while we looke not at the things which are ſeene, but at the things which are not ſeene; for the things which are ſeene, are Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but the things which are not ſeene, are Eternall: wherefore ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18516:77"/>all hinderances apart, with cheerefulneſſe of ſpirit, take up the Croſſe of CHRIST, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage thy feeble ſpirit, with the ſaying of the Apoſtle PAVL: The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this Life, are not comparable to the joyes that ſhall bee heereafter:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> having therefore theſe promiſes, cleanſe your ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holineſſe in the feare of GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:18516:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> That Man ought to bee wonne to follow Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in reſpect of the Eternall Happineſſe.</head>
               <p>HAving now ſet before thee,<note place="margin">Deut. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> Life and good. Death and evill: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire thee, to chooſe Life, that both thou and thy ſeed mayeſt live, for having beheld, the deceiveablenes of worldly pleaſures, and how this momentany feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is attended on, by ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and her Confederates, me thinks thou ſhouldeſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18516:78"/>be weary of this houſe of Clay, ſcituated in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of miſeries, which hourely produceth Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that ravenouſly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to prey on thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy mind from theſe fleeting delights, elevate thy thoughts to Heaven, and contemplate with thy ſelfe, of thoſe Coeleſtiall pleaſures; note the beauty of the place, the gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the company, and the durableneſſe of that Happineſse, which is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; for the beautie of this place, this Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> looke into the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> and thou ſhalt finde; It hath the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18516:79"/>glory of GOD, the light thereof to be like a Iaſper ſtone, cleere as Chryſtall; glorious muſt it needs bee, when the Wall is of Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the City of pure gold, cleare like glaſſe, and the Foundations of the Wall garniſhed with all manner of precious ſtones; the twelve Gates were twelve Pearles; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeverall gate, was of one pearle;<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>15</hi>
                  </note> for the company, there are Angels, and Martyrs, with the foure and twenty Elders, that offer up golden Vials full of odours, which are the Prayers of Saints; but, which is chiefe of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, there will be GOD
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18516:79"/>himſelfe who will bee a Looking-Glaſſe to the eyes of his Elect, Muſicke to theyr eares, Nectar and Ambroſia to their Palates, odoriferous Balſamum to theyr Smelling; There thou ſhalt ſee, the variety and beauty of the ſeaſons, the pleaſantneſſe of the Spring, the brightneſſe of Summer, the fruitfulneſſe of Autumne, and the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of Winter, and there ſhall bee whatſoever may delight thy ſences, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faculty of thy Soule; there will be, the fulneſſe of light to thy underſtanding, the aboundance of Peace to thy will, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Eternity to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18516:80"/>thy memory; there, the Wiſedome of SALOMON, ſhall ſeeme ignorance; there, the beauty of AB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SASOM ſhall ſeeme defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; there, the ſtrength of SAMPSOM, ſhall ſeeme weakeneſſe; there, the long life of METHV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SALEM, ſhall ſeeme a ſpan; there, the Riches of CRoeSVS, ſhall ſeeme droſſe: for there, thou mayſt worthily call the treaſures of all Emperors and Kings, ſtarke poverty and beggery.</p>
               <p>Theſe things beeing thus? Why ſhouldeſt thou O man! delight to begge, and live of Almes, when thou ſhalt finde ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18516:80"/>in Heaven, looke upon thy ſelfe and conſider, how the Lord hath beſtowed upon thee a countenance of Majeſty, with thy face erected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and thy eye-lids to move upwards, thereby to teach thee, that thou wert not formed, to ſpend thy dayes in the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cares of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome world, but to aſpire to that true Happines, that maketh all the other Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Marke the Sea-mans Needle, whoſe nature of that Iron is, that in what part it hath touched the Loadſtone, that part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes looketh towards
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18516:81"/>the North, and remaineth unſetled, till it hath found the Pole: even ſo hath God created Man, and hath infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into him a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and readineſſe, that hee ſhould alwayes looke to his Maker, as to the Pole and onely true happines.</p>
               <p>When the Children of <hi>Jſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, were ſtung by fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, none could live, but thoſe, that looked up to that brazen Serpent, which MOSES erected; ſo no man beeing ſtung by thoſe fiery Serpents of ſin, can live; but thoſe, that by the eye of Faith looke up to CHRIST IESVS,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18516:81"/>beholding him, dying upon the Croſſe, and applying his death and merits, to their otherwiſe deadly-wounded Soule, whereby that Vlcer is cured and they aſſured of life.</p>
               <p>After ADAM had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in eating the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> GOD ſent him to Till the Earth, out of which he was taken; but the ſoule of man was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into him by the breath of God;<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cogitations of thy heart and Soule bee turned towards him, from whence it had the beeing, ſeeing, as ſayth Saint AVGVSTINE: There is nothing more bleſſed, than
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18516:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:18516:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:18516:83"/>this life, where there is no feare of Poverty, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity of Sickneſſe, no deceipts of the Divell, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Death of body or Soule, but, a pleaſant life through the guift of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, then there ſhall be no miſchiefes, no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, but all agreement; becauſe there ſhall be one concord, of all the Saints, peace and joy imbrace all things.</p>
               <p>What is it, that thou canſt deſire heere upon Earth, that thou ſhalt not there freely poſſeſſe? If thou defireſt pleaſures, lift up thy heart and ſee how delightfull that Good is, that contayneth in it, the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18516:83"/>delight and pleaſure of all good things? If this life created doth pleaſe thee, how much more ſhall that life pleaſe thee, which hath created all things? If health given make thee merry, how much more ſhall he make thee merry, that giveth all health? If the knowledge of the Creatures bee ſweet, how much more ſweeter ſhall the Creator himſelfe be? if beauty bee acceptable unto thee, it is he, at whoſe beauty, the Sunne and Moone admire; the glory of which, was ſo great, that when MOSES went up to the Mount, though he ſaw but the hinder part
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18516:84"/>thereof, his Face became ſo bright and ſhining, that the Iſraelites could not behold him; what ſhould I ſtand longer to ſet forth the beauty of that, which if I had the tongue of Men and Angels, I could not doe; for as the Apoſtle fayth;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> Eye hath not ſeene, Eare hath not heard, neyther hath it entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of Man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou then chooſe with the Prodigall Sonne, to eate Huskes with the Swine, rather than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne home to thy Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, will not all
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18516:84"/>theſe delights move thee, nor cauſe thee to deſire it; it may bee thou art time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, knowing thy owne unworthineſſe; but bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the words of thy Saviour, who ſeeing thy faint heartedneſſe, ſayth: Feare not little flocke,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> for it is your fathers pleaſure to give you a Kingdome. Thou art one of the flocke, and this Kingdome is prepared for thee; why doſt thou not long to take poſſeſſion of thy owne, pu chaſed for thee by CHRIST, who though hee be thy Elder brother; yet thou ſhalt bee co-heyre with him, whoſe love, thou mayſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18516:85"/>ſee expreſſed, by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite care; for in his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to his Father for his Diſciples, he remembred thee, when he ſayd, I pray not for theſe alone,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>117.</hi>
                  </note> but for thoſe that ſhall beleeve on me, that they may all be one as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, and the glory which thou haſt given mee, I have given them, that they may bee one even as wee are one, I will alſo, that thoſe thou haſt given mee, bee with me.</p>
               <p>Canſt thou now have any doubts or waverings in thy Mind? Repayre unto him, and in true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of Soule confeſſe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18516:85"/>thy ſelfe unto him, and ſay; Father I have ſinned againſt Heaven and againſt thee, and I am no more worthy to bee called thy Sonne: This done, doubt not but hee will imbrace thee in the Armes of his Mercy, the Ring and Robe ſhall be brought, and the fatted Calfe ſhall be kild: for there is more joy in Heaven, over one ſinner that repenteth, than of ninety and nine juſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: It is a place prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee, before the Foundations of the World were layd. O happy Soule! that art made poſſeſſor of this bleſſedneſſe! How art thou able to behold any
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18516:86"/>thing in this life, with true contentment, having ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly beheld this; though thou didſt dayly ſuffer torments, if for a long time thou didſt indure Hell it ſelfe, ſo that at the length thou mighteſt ſee CHRIST in his glory, and injoy this bleſſedneſse, and haue ſociety with the Saints; were it not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy all Sufferings? All Bitternes? and all Croſſes, that thou mighteſt be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all this good. At laſt, what though the world account not of thee, but deride thee for thy vertuous living? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ELIZEVS the Prophet of the Lord, who
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18516:86"/>was mocked and called <hi>Bald-head,</hi> in contempt; Reſolve with thy ſelfe, no ſooner to enter into the path of Godlineſse, but ſuch is the malitiouſneſse of thy Mortall Enemie, that hee will ſet his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the way agaiuſt thee; that if it bee poſſible, they may hinder thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and turne thee backe againe into the broad way of Errors, that leadeth to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>No ſooner did SAVL Propheſie, but the wicked and the men of BELIAL, had him in deriſion, who better affected, then PAVL the Apoſtle, whilſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned a Perſecutor of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18516:87"/>CHRIST in his members, and carried with him the authority of the High Prieſts, to ſtrengthen his proceedings; but no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was he converted, but how many enimies had he, which ſtreight ſought his deſtruction, hayling him to Priſons, to Scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and to Stonings to death. Yet ſo farre were they from being diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this, as that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for the name of CHRIST.</p>
               <p>When we enter into Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, we profeſſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come CHRISTS ſouldiers, and to fight vnder his ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and is it the part of a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:18516:87"/>Souldier, to flye at the firſt onſet, he that indureth to the end, gaineth not onely the honour, but the reward; nay, the fiercer the aſſault is, the more we ought to oppoſe our ſelues againſt it, and though through the roughnes of the incounter, we may thinke we haue the worſt, yet if with patience wee ſtriue to perſeuer, our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine CHRIST IESVS will be at hand to helpe vs, for carefull is he of his owne, as his owne mouth teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; when he ſaith, to his Father, All thou haſt giuen me, I haue kept, and none of them is loſt. Let all theſe proofes arme thy
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:18516:88"/>minde, to be reſolute in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in goodnes, till thou attaine the end where thou ſhalt gaine the reward of thy abours, and take with theel, the Counſell of the Philoſopher HERMES, who ſayth, It is better, to ſuffer ſhame for vertuous dealing, then to win ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by vicious living.</p>
               <p>When SALOMON had builded the Teinple and ſanctified it, none might enter into <hi>Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the holieſt of all, but the Prieſt onely. So none can enter into this Kingdome, which is the true <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum;</hi> but thoſe who haue by a Religious courſe of life,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:18516:88"/>put off the vanities of this world, and cloathed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Robe of CHRISTS Righteouſneſſe, whereby they are Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated &amp; made fit to enter.</p>
               <p>When the Children of <hi>Jſraell</hi> were in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded every day to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Manna, but on the Sabboth they that went to gather, found none for that they were on the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to provide for that day: ſo fayle not thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day of thy life, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Manna, the food of thy ſoule, and to lay vp in ſtore againſt this day of thy reſt, leaſt when thou hopeſt to find, thou become
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18516:89"/>fruſtrate, and ſo thy ſoule ſtarue with want thereof, feede not thy ſelfe with hopes of entertainement, vnleſſe thou haue furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thy ſelfe with the wedding garment, neither thinke to paſse with one that is counterfeit, though neuer ſo neare the colour; for if it be not found the right one, thou ſhalt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and bound hand and foot, and caſt into utter darkeneſse; therefore it is that the Apoſtle ſayth, Examine your ſelves whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee be in the Faith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> prove your ſelves.</p>
               <p>There are many, nay moſt that vnderſtanding the infinitneſee of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:18516:89"/>of this place, that with BALAAM will deſire to dye the death of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,<note place="margin">Numb. <hi>33</hi>
                  </note> but they will not liue the life of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: becauſe they exempt themſelves from many things, in the which the wicked place theyr whole felicity, they accounting this world theyr Heauen, ſhall therefore finde none other hereafter, as in the parable, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſayd to the rich man in Hell; Son remember that thou in thy life-time, received thy good things; they were his, becauſein them conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all his happines: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore poſſeſſing of them here, he could not expect
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:18516:90"/>a future: For as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, Be not deceiued, God is not mocked, for what a man ſoweth, that ſhall he reape; for he that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reape corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, reape life euerlaſting. For true bleſſednes, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth not in meat or drink, or in richneſse of apparell, but in Righteouſnes and Peace, and Ioy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>A man who hath beene long kept from his father and mother, wife or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by impriſonment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once at liberty, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred on his lourney toward
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:18516:90"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, regardeth not neither the length of the way, the weariſomnes of his owne ſteps, nor the dangerouſnes of the places he is to paſſe, but goeth on with cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse and longings, till he attaine the end, and as a ſpurre to whet on his ſpeed, placeth before the eye of his remembrance the ſweete content hee ſhall finde at meeting, can theſe earthly delights cauſe a man to vndergoe ſo many difficulties, and ſhall not the delights which God hath prepared for his and whereof I haue giuen thee a glimpſe, cauſe thee with much more feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to long to attaine to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18516:91"/>this place of happineſse, and ſetting a part all hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances whatſoever, ſix thy eye of Faith vpon thoſe vnſpeakeable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which thy ſoule ſhall then gayne, &amp; in Ioy when thou ſhalt meete with God thy Father, Chriſt Ieſus thy Brother and Sauiour, who hath by the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his love eſpouſed thee vnto himſelfe; and made the poſſeſſor of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where thou ſhalt as ſayth Saint AVGVST. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a certaine imbracing aboue all imbracings.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt find a ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aboue all ſweetneſse, thou ſhalt ſee alight aboue all lights, thou ſhalt ſmell
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:18516:91"/>a ſauour aboue all ſavours, moſt delectable, thou ſhalt heare a voyce aboue all voyces for rarenes, for that voyce doth ſound where no ayre doth moue it, this light doth ſhine, where no place doth receiue it, this ſavour doth ſmell where no blaſt doth carry it, and this imbrace is there touched, where it is not ſundred; to conclude if thou deſireſt to inioy all bleſſedneſse, and to eſcape all kinde of puniſhments, tribulations, and miſeries, there thou ſhalt find liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; freedome from them all. The God of our Lord IESVS CHRIST, the Father of Glory, give vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18516:92"/>vs, the ſpirit of wiſdome &amp; knowledge of him, that the eyes of our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding being inlightned, we may know, what is the hope of his calling, and what the Riches of the Glory of the inheritance of his Saints, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:18516:92"/>
            <head>Of our loſſe by ADAM, and our gayne by CHRIST; The firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was made a living Soule, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> a quickning Spirit; For as in ADAM wee all dye, ſo in CHRIST, ſhall all be made alive. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD</hi> by his Wiſedame,</l>
               <l>and all-ſeeing Pow'r</l>
               <l>Ordained Man</l>
               <l>vnto Eternitie,</l>
               <l>Sathan through malice,</l>
               <l>turnes that ſweet to ſowre,</l>
               <l>Man eating the forbidden Fruit</l>
               <l>muſt Die:</l>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:18516:93"/>
               <l>No remedy was left</l>
               <l>to ſcape this Curſe,</l>
               <l>The ſore ſtill looked on</l>
               <l>became the worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He out of that delightſome</l>
               <l>place is throwne</l>
               <l>To travell in the Warld</l>
               <l>with woe diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Through all his life</l>
               <l>a Pilgrim he is knowne,</l>
               <l>With Cares and Sorrowes,</l>
               <l>and with griefes oppreſt:</l>
               <l>The more he lookes</l>
               <l>into his wretched ſtate,</l>
               <l>The more he rues his fact</l>
               <l>but all too late.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:18516:93"/>
               <l>Whereas he was</l>
               <l>created King of all</l>
               <l>The Creatures</l>
               <l>God on Earth created had,</l>
               <l>His Glory bated is</l>
               <l>by this his Fall,</l>
               <l>No creature now on Earth</l>
               <l>remaines ſo bad:</l>
               <l>The ſenceleſſe Beaſt</l>
               <l>the ſence of this hath found,</l>
               <l>And having Man poſſeſt</l>
               <l>with death doth wound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Earth diſdaines</l>
               <l>to yeeld to him her ſtrength</l>
               <l>But pricking Thornes</l>
               <l>and Brambles forth doth ſend,</l>
               <l>Till with his ſweat</l>
               <l>and labours ſhe at length</l>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:18516:94"/>
               <l>Onely for ſuſtenance</l>
               <l>ſome food doth lend:</l>
               <l>Thus he that was</l>
               <l>a heauenly Creature form'd,</l>
               <l>By diſobedience</l>
               <l>to a wretch is turn'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all the Trees</l>
               <l>that in the Garden grew,</l>
               <l>He onely was forbidden</l>
               <l>that alone,</l>
               <l>His Wife from that obedience</l>
               <l>ſoone him drew,</l>
               <l>And taſte thereof</l>
               <l>he did although but one:</l>
               <l>O wretched man!</l>
               <l>what haſt thou loſt hereby</l>
               <l>Wicked woman</l>
               <l>to cauſe thy husband dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:18516:94"/>
               <l>T'is not ſaying,</l>
               <l>the Serpent thee deceiu'd,</l>
               <l>That can excuſe the fault</l>
               <l>thou didſt commit;</l>
               <l>For of all Ioyes</l>
               <l>thou haſt thy ſelfe bereau'd,</l>
               <l>And by thy Conſcience</l>
               <l>thou doſt ſtand convict.</l>
               <l>Thy husband not alone</l>
               <l>the fault muſt rue,</l>
               <l>A puniſhment for ſinne</l>
               <l>to thee is due.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For as thou now conceiues</l>
               <l>thy ſeed in ſinne,</l>
               <l>So in great ſorrow</l>
               <l>thou muſt bring it foorth,</l>
               <l>The gaine which thou</l>
               <l>by that ſame fruit didſt winne,</l>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:18516:95"/>
               <l>Thou now doſt find</l>
               <l>to bee but little worth:</l>
               <l>Obedience to thy Husband</l>
               <l>yeeld thou muſt,</l>
               <l>And both muſt Dye</l>
               <l>and turned be to Duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Truth ſometimes</l>
               <l>is vſed by the Divell</l>
               <l>When as he ſayd,</l>
               <l>Your eyes, ſhould opened bee,</l>
               <l>And that you ſhould</l>
               <l>diſcerne the good from euill,</l>
               <l>When you the Fruit had taſted</l>
               <l>of that tree:</l>
               <l>But hee told not</l>
               <l>your actions, ſhould be ſinne,</l>
               <l>And Death ſhould be the good</l>
               <l>which you ſhould winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:18516:95"/>
               <l>For now your ſtrength</l>
               <l>to weakeneſſe turned is,</l>
               <l>You know the Good</l>
               <l>but have no powre to chuſe't,</l>
               <l>Your eyes is ope, to ſee</l>
               <l>your owne amiſſe,</l>
               <l>And to behold the bliſſe</l>
               <l>you have refus'd:</l>
               <l>You ſee your nakedneſſe</l>
               <l>made vilde by Sinne,</l>
               <l>And now ſeekes for a place</l>
               <l>to hide you in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But O alas!</l>
               <l>your deeds diſcover'd are,</l>
               <l>You naked lye</l>
               <l>to thoſe all-ſeeing eyes,</l>
               <l>He viewes your actions</l>
               <l>and doth ſee you bare,</l>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:18516:96"/>
               <l>Bare of all Goodneſſe,</l>
               <l>vilde deformities:</l>
               <l>And in your ſelves</l>
               <l>you have no power to mend,</l>
               <l>For all your ſtrength, is ſinne</l>
               <l>Sathan doth lend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſeizes on your ſickneſſe</l>
               <l>Griefes and Feares,</l>
               <l>Which night and day</l>
               <l>with trouble will torment;</l>
               <l>Your ſweet Delights,</l>
               <l>are turned all to teares,</l>
               <l>And now what you haue done,</l>
               <l>with woerepent!</l>
               <l>Nothing but Griefes and Feares</l>
               <l>and ſad annoyes,</l>
               <l>You now poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>in ſtead of endleſſe Ioyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:18516:96"/>
               <l>You were immortall,</l>
               <l>but are mortall made;</l>
               <l>You were created pure,</l>
               <l>but now are vilde;</l>
               <l>Your ſplendant Glories</l>
               <l>turned all to ſhade,</l>
               <l>Your Innocence</l>
               <l>the Deuill hath beguilde:</l>
               <l>You were created</l>
               <l>Children of the Lord,</l>
               <l>But now are loathſome Dung,</l>
               <l>to be abhorr'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which way, can you</l>
               <l>recouer this your loſſe?</l>
               <l>What friend have you,</l>
               <l>that will this great debt pay?</l>
               <l>Can you gaine, pure gold</l>
               <l>from filthy droſſe?</l>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:18516:97"/>
               <l>Or have you power</l>
               <l>to call againe that Day;</l>
               <l>No, you are in</l>
               <l>a laborinth of woe,</l>
               <l>And endleſſe is the maze</l>
               <l>in which you goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet courage Woman,</l>
               <l>whoſe weake ſpirit's dead,</l>
               <l>GOD in his love</l>
               <l>a helpe for thee hath found,</l>
               <l>Bee ſure thy Seed</l>
               <l>ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHRIST</hi> by his Death</l>
               <l>ſhall Sathan deadly wound:</l>
               <l>This Lyon of <hi>Iudea</hi>
               </l>
               <l>reſiſt who can,</l>
               <l>In him is bleſt</l>
               <l>the whole Off-ſpring of man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:18516:97"/>
               <l>This Promiſe in due time</l>
               <l>fulfill'd hath GOD,</l>
               <l>Vnto the comfort</l>
               <l>of each mortall weight;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHRIST</hi> payes our Debt</l>
               <l>hee's beaten with that rod</l>
               <l>That doth belong</l>
               <l>vnto our Soules of right:</l>
               <l>His Fathers wrath</l>
               <l>was powred vpon him,</l>
               <l>Which doth belong</l>
               <l>as due to vs for Sinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hee dy'd vpon the Croſſe</l>
               <l>and conquered Death.</l>
               <l>That though wee dye</l>
               <l>yet live againe wee muſt,</l>
               <l>He buried was</l>
               <l>and riſen is from Earth,</l>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:18516:98"/>
               <l>And raignes with God</l>
               <l>in Heaven amongſt the Iuſt:</l>
               <l>With him, our Soules and Bodies</l>
               <l>rais'd hath hee,</l>
               <l>And from deaths thraldome</l>
               <l>now, hath ſet vs free:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This cauſeth Sathan</l>
               <l>ſtir himſelfe amaine,</l>
               <l>To ſee, if he can winne</l>
               <l>what he hath loſt:</l>
               <l>He ſtrives to make</l>
               <l>our overthrow his gaine.</l>
               <l>He ſtormeth now,</l>
               <l>that he, by <hi>CHRIST</hi> is crost:</l>
               <l>And to his ayde,</l>
               <l>he all his forces drawes,</l>
               <l>That he may cauſe vs</l>
               <l>to obey his Lawes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:18516:98"/>
               <l>Whole Armies of his Furies</l>
               <l>forth he ſends,</l>
               <l>In ſhape transformed,</l>
               <l>to delude our mindes;</l>
               <l>And vnto them</l>
               <l>his greateſt force he lends,</l>
               <l>To ſeize, where fitteſt</l>
               <l>for his turne he findes:</l>
               <l>He marks, to what men</l>
               <l>are by nature given,</l>
               <l>And vnto that,</l>
               <l>he turnes his Compaſſe euen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sathan's deceipts</l>
               <l>are covered, all with ſmiles.</l>
               <l>That ſinne ſeemes pleaſing,</l>
               <l>which our Soules deſtroyes,</l>
               <l>With quaint allurements,</l>
               <l>hee man ſtill beguiles.</l>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:18516:99"/>
               <l>With ſweet delights</l>
               <l>he breeds Mans ſad annoyes,</l>
               <l>He imitates a Poyſon</l>
               <l>rarely framed,</l>
               <l>But once being taken</l>
               <l>all the life blood's ſtained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Old and craftie</l>
               <l>is our Enemy growne,</l>
               <l>He knowes all Fiſh</l>
               <l>at one baite will not bite,</l>
               <l>Hee'l try a thouſand wayes</l>
               <l>to gaine his owne,</l>
               <l>He will not leave</l>
               <l>till he the marke hits right.</l>
               <l>Some with Drunkenneſſe,</l>
               <l>Murders, Luſt beſide,</l>
               <l>Others with Idleneſſe,</l>
               <l>exeſsive Pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:18516:99"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>BACCHVS</hi> that drunken God</l>
               <l>from Hell comes forth,</l>
               <l>And reeling here and there</l>
               <l>few ſcapes his knockes,</l>
               <l>Who ſhunnes his blowes</l>
               <l>eſteem'd are of no worth,</l>
               <l>One Drunkard at anothers</l>
               <l>weakeneſſe mockes:</l>
               <l>What <hi>ISAIAH</hi> ſaith,</l>
               <l>thereon they never thinke;</l>
               <l>Woe bee to them!</l>
               <l>are ſtrong to pw'r in drinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>GOD, in his love</l>
               <l>form'd all things for mans vſe,</l>
               <l>That for his Comfort</l>
               <l>they might daily be,</l>
               <l>But they prove poyſon</l>
               <l>through mans vilde abuſe,</l>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:18516:100"/>
               <l>Sinne changeth all</l>
               <l>into deformity:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>PAVL</hi> for mans health,</l>
               <l>to drinke Wine doth adviſe.</l>
               <l>But through exceſſe,</l>
               <l>both Soule and Body dyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man, by this Sinne</l>
               <l>more vile is, than a Beaſt;</l>
               <l>For but ſufficient,</l>
               <l>they will never take,</l>
               <l>Mans ſences fayles him</l>
               <l>ſinnes are ſtill increaſt,</l>
               <l>He tracing vices,</l>
               <l>doth all good forſake:</l>
               <l>In Drunkenneſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOT</hi> doth to Inceſt fall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>NOAN</hi> in his Wine,</l>
               <l>his ſecrets ſhewes to all</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:18516:100"/>
               <l>Then Luſt, and Murther</l>
               <l>hands together take,</l>
               <l>Like full fed Beaſts,</l>
               <l>they neigh at neighbours wife,</l>
               <l>Stolne bread is ſweet,</l>
               <l>hid water theyr thirſts ſlake,</l>
               <l>They fall to Murther,</l>
               <l>through diſcord and ſtrife.</l>
               <l>For when mans reaſon fayles,</l>
               <l>to guide his will;</l>
               <l>He into miſchiefe,</l>
               <l>runneth headlong ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt people takes</l>
               <l>Idleneſſe, for no ſinne:</l>
               <l>Thus in Simplicitie,</l>
               <l>Sathan deludes,</l>
               <l>That precious time is loſt,</l>
               <l>that Grace might winne.</l>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:18516:101"/>
               <l>And want of action,</l>
               <l>many ſinnes includes:</l>
               <l>That minde, which vnto</l>
               <l>Idleneſſe giues way,</l>
               <l>Doth open lye</l>
               <l>to bee the Devils prey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>DAVID</hi> vnto eaſe</l>
               <l>himſelfe had giuen,</l>
               <l>His eyes extravagantly</l>
               <l>looke about,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VRIAH's</hi> wife he ſpyeth</l>
               <l>in the Even,</l>
               <l>He muſt, and did enioy her</l>
               <l>without doubt:</l>
               <l>Sathan by this his fall</l>
               <l>more ſtrength doth gaine,</l>
               <l>For <hi>DAVID</hi> bids</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VRIAH</hi> ſhould be ſlaine.</l>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:18516:101"/>
               <l>Thus by one meanes or other</l>
               <l>Sathan ſnares</l>
               <l>Mans ſoule in Sinne,</l>
               <l>and hudwinck'd tills him on;</l>
               <l>His cup of Gold</l>
               <l>is filled vp with teares</l>
               <l>A bitter pittance</l>
               <l>to theyr ſweetes belong:</l>
               <l>Pride, in it ſelfe</l>
               <l>doth beare a poyſon'd breath,</l>
               <l>No Sinne ſo ſmall</l>
               <l>but puniſht is with Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſinn's thought leaſt</l>
               <l>that's ſpent in trimming fine</l>
               <l>That Carkaſſe vilde,</l>
               <l>on which the Wormes muſt prey,</l>
               <l>They thinke not how</l>
               <l>theyr hungry Soule doth pine,</l>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:18516:102"/>
               <l>They count not</l>
               <l>of theyr reckoning at last day.</l>
               <l>But time of Grace, once loſt,</l>
               <l>is without call,</l>
               <l>So headlong to deſtruction</l>
               <l>they doe fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pride, of all other</l>
               <l>ſembleth moſt the Divell?</l>
               <l>'Twas Pride, threw Sathan</l>
               <l>downe from Heaven to Hell:</l>
               <l>'Twas Pride, that Author was</l>
               <l>of all mans euill:</l>
               <l>'Twas Pride, made <hi>EVE</hi>
               </l>
               <l>deſire ſtill to excell;</l>
               <l>When Sathan ſaid,</l>
               <l>as Gods, you then ſhall be;</l>
               <l>Incontinent, ſhe taſted</l>
               <l>of that Tree.</l>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:18516:102"/>
               <l>This Lep'rous ſinne,</l>
               <l>infected ſo the bloud,</l>
               <l>That through her off-ſpring,</l>
               <l>it hath who ly runne;</l>
               <l>Before the child can know,</l>
               <l>the bad from good;</l>
               <l>It ſtraight is proud,</l>
               <l>Nature, this hure hath done.</l>
               <l>A female ſinne,</l>
               <l>it counted was to be,</l>
               <l>But now Hermaphrodite,</l>
               <l>proved is ſhee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like <hi>IVDAS,</hi> Sathan</l>
               <l>with each mortall deales,</l>
               <l>His haile, is Hate,</l>
               <l>his flattering kiſſe, is death,</l>
               <l>He every where</l>
               <l>ſtill watching, creeping ſteales,</l>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:18516:103"/>
               <l>With armed troupes</l>
               <l>to ſtifle his ſoules breath:</l>
               <l>His Syrens ſongs,</l>
               <l>mans mortall Death intends,</l>
               <l>And hee muſt Dye</l>
               <l>that thereto his care lends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As a Phyſition</l>
               <l>with his Patient ſtill</l>
               <l>Applyes his potion</l>
               <l>as he findes it fit;</l>
               <l>Giuing to ſome, more ſtrong</l>
               <l>becauſe theyr ill</l>
               <l>Diſpoſed body,</l>
               <l>oft requireth it:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo, doth Sathan</l>
               <l>with each Creature deale,</l>
               <l>But his is meant for death</l>
               <l>and not to heale.</l>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:18516:103"/>
               <l>Nature and Sathan,</l>
               <l>are ſworne Brothers ſtill,</l>
               <l>For neyther of them</l>
               <l>moveth man to good;</l>
               <l>By Nature, we incline</l>
               <l>to all that's ill,</l>
               <l>Which runneth through</l>
               <l>our body with our blood:</l>
               <l>And by our Nature</l>
               <l>oft he vs aſſailes,</l>
               <l>And through our weakneſſe</l>
               <l>he oft times prevailes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He, by our Nature ſees</l>
               <l>to what we bend,</l>
               <l>Whether to goodneſſe</l>
               <l>or to miſchiefes run;</l>
               <l>And if he ſind man ayme</l>
               <l>at the beſt end,</l>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:18516:104"/>
               <l>Then ſtrives he for to marre</l>
               <l>all he hath done,</l>
               <l>And by a pride of Goodnes</l>
               <l>makes him be,</l>
               <l>Towards his God,</l>
               <l>like the proud Phariſie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The bleſſings, God to man</l>
               <l>doth often giue,</l>
               <l>As beautie, health, riches,</l>
               <l>honours and fame,</l>
               <l>That he, in thankefulnes</l>
               <l>for them ſhouldſt liue,</l>
               <l>Still vſing them</l>
               <l>to glorifie his Name:</l>
               <l>Sathan tranſeformeth</l>
               <l>all this vnto ſinne,</l>
               <l>Through vilde abuſe,</l>
               <l>or conſidence therein.</l>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:18516:104"/>
               <l>This thing, the Scripture</l>
               <l>euidently ſhowes,</l>
               <l>By <hi>DAVIDs</hi> numbering</l>
               <l>of Iſraell,</l>
               <l>Whereby he thought</l>
               <l>more truſt for to repoſe</l>
               <l>In his great army,</l>
               <l>this to ſinne befell:</l>
               <l>And drawing on</l>
               <l>Gods Iudgement for the ſame,</l>
               <l>A heavy plague</l>
               <l>he on his Realine did gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is a ſinne, on which</l>
               <l>ſmall count is made,</l>
               <l>And that is Diſobedience;</l>
               <l>for which ſinne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>SAMVEL</hi> the Prophet</l>
               <l>vnto <hi>SAVL</hi> once ſayd;</l>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:18516:105"/>
               <l>From being King</l>
               <l>God had reiected him:</l>
               <l>When as he <hi>AMELECK</hi>
               </l>
               <l>all ſhould have ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Sathan mov'd him</l>
               <l>to let the beſt remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſinne, ſo great</l>
               <l>in Gods pure ſight doth ſeeme,</l>
               <l>As that the Prophet</l>
               <l>plainly doth him tell:</l>
               <l>The Lord, no better</l>
               <l>of it doth eſteeme;</l>
               <l>Then, of vild Witchcraft</l>
               <l>which in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Lord commanded</l>
               <l>baniſh'd quite to be;</l>
               <l>This, like to that</l>
               <l>and to Idolatrie.</l>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:18516:105"/>
               <l>This onely ſinne</l>
               <l>on all Mankinde did draw,</l>
               <l>Gods heavy wrath,</l>
               <l>for this, we ſuffer ſtill.</l>
               <l>By <hi>ADAMS</hi> breaking</l>
               <l>Gods commanded Law;</l>
               <l>Sinne with a poyſned dart</l>
               <l>our ſoules did kill:</l>
               <l>For through the breach thereof</l>
               <l>there entred death,</l>
               <l>For ſo 'twas ſentenced</l>
               <l>by Gods owne breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O this ſame ſinne,</l>
               <l>as an accuſing one</l>
               <l>On all occaſions</l>
               <l>ſtill it guilty ſayth:</l>
               <l>Fulfill Gods Law, who did</l>
               <l>nere yet, was knowne,</l>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:18516:106"/>
               <l>But <hi>CHRIST</hi> who came</l>
               <l>for to appeaſe Gods wrath:</l>
               <l>Then by his Law</l>
               <l>we all convicted ſtand,</l>
               <l>And howerly may</l>
               <l>looke for Gods wrath at hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deferring off Repentance</l>
               <l>is a bayte</l>
               <l>So cloſely layd</l>
               <l>by that old Enemy,</l>
               <l>That ſew doth diue</l>
               <l>the depth of his deceit,</l>
               <l>But vnprouided</l>
               <l>many men doe die:</l>
               <l>He bids them on the good theefe</l>
               <l>their eyes caſt,</l>
               <l>Who neuer did, repent him</l>
               <l>till the laſt.</l>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:18516:106"/>
               <l>O ſlye, deceitfull</l>
               <l>cruell enemy,</l>
               <l>How deadly, is thy hatred</l>
               <l>to vs all</l>
               <l>Thou <hi>EHVD</hi> like</l>
               <l>hides that will cauſe vs dye,</l>
               <l>And ſith thou fell'ſt</l>
               <l>thou aym'ſt ſtill at our fall:</l>
               <l>In Paradice the Tree</l>
               <l>death did vs give,</l>
               <l>But by the Tree</l>
               <l>in Golgotha, we live.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From a decline in goodneſſe</l>
               <l>let each Soule,</l>
               <l>With heedfull care</l>
               <l>ſtill ſtudy to beware;</l>
               <l>Leaſt in the end</l>
               <l>for it he doth condole,</l>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:18516:107"/>
               <l>When as his foote</l>
               <l>is fettered in the ſnare:</l>
               <l>Who once his hand</l>
               <l>vpon the Plough doth lay,</l>
               <l>Muſt by no meanes</l>
               <l>looke backe another way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eaſie it is, to plunge</l>
               <l>our ſelues in ſinne,</l>
               <l>But, O alas!</l>
               <l>hard to get forth againe;</l>
               <l>If by our faults</l>
               <l>our Soules be black with in,</l>
               <l>We then ſhall finde</l>
               <l>all his deluſions vaine;</l>
               <l>His voyce of peace</l>
               <l>all peace doth from vs take,</l>
               <l>Then ſhun that hearbe</l>
               <l>where vnder lyes the Snake.</l>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:18516:107"/>
               <l>Man ought at all times</l>
               <l>have a carefull eye;</l>
               <l>For many are the Snares</l>
               <l>which Sathan layes:</l>
               <l>When leaſt he thinketh on</l>
               <l>to cauſe him dye,</l>
               <l>He hides the bayte</l>
               <l>the which mans ſoule betrayes:</l>
               <l>Of eaſe and pleaſures</l>
               <l>he will alwayes tell,</l>
               <l>But his ſmooth path</l>
               <l>the brode way is to Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who on this Panthers skinne</l>
               <l>doth gazing ſtand,</l>
               <l>Had need beware</l>
               <l>who lyes in wayte to catch,</l>
               <l>Who holdes a Woolfe by th'eares</l>
               <l>but with one hand,</l>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:18516:108"/>
               <l>Muſt with the other</l>
               <l>muzzell vp his chaps:</l>
               <l>If better thou doſt get</l>
               <l>leave not off ſo,</l>
               <l>But of all meanes to hurt,</l>
               <l>deprive thy Foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That man, the which</l>
               <l>his Enemy foyl'd hath,</l>
               <l>Muſt ſtraight vnarme him</l>
               <l>leaſt he gather ſtrength;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>BENHADADS</hi> ſervants</l>
               <l>after <hi>AHABS</hi> wrath,</l>
               <l>With feyned words</l>
               <l>did come to him at length</l>
               <l>And from his kindneſſe</l>
               <l>they advantage draw,</l>
               <l>For he, that fear'd to dye</l>
               <l>now made a Law.</l>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:18516:108"/>
               <l>By his Example</l>
               <l>let vs warned bee,</l>
               <l>Gods Prophet vnto <hi>AHAB</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſtraight doth come,</l>
               <l>And ſayd, Becauſe from death</l>
               <l>thou didſt him free,</l>
               <l>Be ſure thy life ſhall ſtand</l>
               <l>in his lifes roome.</l>
               <l>Leave thou not Sathan,</l>
               <l>till thou ſeeſt him dead,</l>
               <l>And <hi>IABL</hi> like,</l>
               <l>kill <hi>SISERA</hi> in the head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He aymes not at thy ſlips,</l>
               <l>but overthrow;</l>
               <l>Small hurts content him not,</l>
               <l>he life would ſpill:</l>
               <l>With ſlight advantages,</l>
               <l>he will not goe:</l>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:18516:109"/>
               <l>When thou ſecureſt art,</l>
               <l>he waites to kill:</l>
               <l>And <hi>IOAS</hi> like</l>
               <l>of thy health he'll inquire,</l>
               <l>But 'tis not life,</l>
               <l>but death he doth deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Can this old Serpent,</l>
               <l>this deceiuing Divell,</l>
               <l>Get in his head,</l>
               <l>then follow ſhall his tayle,</l>
               <l>If man but yeeld a little,</l>
               <l>vnto evill,</l>
               <l>Sinne will increaſe,</l>
               <l>though creeping like a Snaile.</l>
               <l>And if vnto a Cuſtome,</l>
               <l>it doth come,</l>
               <l>He feeles it not,</l>
               <l>his ſoule is now growne num.</l>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:18516:109"/>
               <l>All Sathan baites,</l>
               <l>are glittering to the eye,</l>
               <l>He leades man on,</l>
               <l>in a delight ſome traine:</l>
               <l>Till death arreſts them,</l>
               <l>ſaying thou muſt dye,</l>
               <l>And then he lets them ſee</l>
               <l>all was but vaine:</l>
               <l>Then in the vgli'ſt forme</l>
               <l>hee ſhewes them all,</l>
               <l>That into Deſperation</l>
               <l>man may fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now having ſuch a ſtrong</l>
               <l>and powerfull foe,</l>
               <l>What need hath Man</l>
               <l>with heedfull care to watch,</l>
               <l>Leaſt on a ſuddaine</l>
               <l>he from hence doe goe,</l>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:18516:110"/>
               <l>For Death as well</l>
               <l>doth lye in wayt to catch:</l>
               <l>Who proves a welcome gueſt</l>
               <l>to a good man,</l>
               <l>For vnprovided, come</l>
               <l>he never can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deaths ghaſtly lookes</l>
               <l>to a gtod man ſeemes ſweet,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill prepared hath</l>
               <l>for that his end,</l>
               <l>As <hi>ESAY IACOB,</hi> did</l>
               <l>embracing meet,</l>
               <l>So doth he death</l>
               <l>accounting him his friend:</l>
               <l>If teares doe fall</l>
               <l>they are not ſhed through feares</l>
               <l>For ioy he's come</l>
               <l>forceth from him thoſe teares.</l>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:18516:110"/>
               <l>Can he expect Death</l>
               <l>Enemie to be,</l>
               <l>Who by his Preſent</l>
               <l>hath his force alayd:</l>
               <l>He ſent before good workes,</l>
               <l>much Charity,</l>
               <l>Bleſſings of Orphants</l>
               <l>which for him have pray'd:</l>
               <l>His ſighs and teares,</l>
               <l>appeaſed hath his King,</l>
               <l>And this ſuppoſed Foe</l>
               <l>glad newes doth bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Death is our guide</l>
               <l>vnto Eternall bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Portall of Heaven,</l>
               <l>by which we enter muſt,</l>
               <l>The Ladder reaching</l>
               <l>a true happineſſe,</l>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:18516:111"/>
               <l>Which bringeth man</l>
               <l>to live amongſt the Iuſt:</l>
               <l>By him we come</l>
               <l>Gods glorious face to ſee,</l>
               <l>From which by life</l>
               <l>deprin'd we ſtill ſhall bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our fleſh a priſon is</l>
               <l>vnto our ſoule,</l>
               <l>Which doth deprive it</l>
               <l>of that heavenly light;</l>
               <l>With ſpirituall groanes &amp; ſighs</l>
               <l>it doth condole,</l>
               <l>Till it attaine</l>
               <l>vnto that wiſhed ſight:</l>
               <l>Death is the key</l>
               <l>vnlocks our miſery;</l>
               <l>Looſeth our bonds</l>
               <l>and gives vs liberty.</l>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:18516:111"/>
               <l>Death's fangs are par'd</l>
               <l>his bitter potions ſweet,</l>
               <l>His edge abaited</l>
               <l>all his hurt is done,</l>
               <l>A godly man</l>
               <l>moſt kindly he doth meete,</l>
               <l>And of a Foe</l>
               <l>he is a Friend become:</l>
               <l>His ſtrooke is like</l>
               <l>the ſtriking of a veine,</l>
               <l>By which ſmall ſmart</l>
               <l>ſick men theyr health doe gaine:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Death is the ending</l>
               <l>of our dayes, not life,</l>
               <l>For having clos'd theſe eyes</l>
               <l>we wake to live,</l>
               <l>Death having finiſht</l>
               <l>once this mortall ſtrife,</l>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:18516:112"/>
               <l>Our Faith in <hi>CHRIST</hi>
               </l>
               <l>new life to vs doth give:</l>
               <l>Our Night is paſt</l>
               <l>our Day ſtar doth appeare,</l>
               <l>Our Cloud is vaniſh'd</l>
               <l>and our Morne ſhines cleare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ends all ſorrowes,</l>
               <l>now all griefes are done,</l>
               <l>Sinne takes his leave</l>
               <l>and weakneſſe hath his end;</l>
               <l>And now behold</l>
               <l>our Iubilee is come,</l>
               <l>The Harueſt of our labors</l>
               <l>we attend:</l>
               <l>Death's potion onely</l>
               <l>bitter is in ſhow,</l>
               <l>The taſte once paſt</l>
               <l>no operation ſo.</l>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:18516:112"/>
               <l>Mans Glaſſe once run</l>
               <l>his flower of Life once dead,</l>
               <l>That vapor vaniſh'd</l>
               <l>and that ſpan once graſp'd,</l>
               <l>His breath once failing</l>
               <l>all his body's Lead,</l>
               <l>In ſenceleſſe, coldneſſe</l>
               <l>all his parts are claſp'd:</l>
               <l>He came from earth,</l>
               <l>earth houſe-roome now him gives.</l>
               <l>His ſpirit from God</l>
               <l>with God for ever lives.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The carnall wicked</l>
               <l>worldly minded men,</l>
               <l>Who in this life</l>
               <l>their whole content have plac'd</l>
               <l>Doth tremble, when Death</l>
               <l>mention'd is to them,</l>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:18516:113"/>
               <l>Becauſe by him</l>
               <l>all Ioyes from them are chaſed:</l>
               <l>Their eaſe and pleaſures</l>
               <l>changed quite will be,</l>
               <l>All mirth is daſh'd</l>
               <l>by preſent miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſight of him</l>
               <l>vnto their mindes doe bring</l>
               <l>Remembrance of their ſinnes</l>
               <l>they ſlightly paſt,</l>
               <l>The which with woe</l>
               <l>their ſoules doe ſorely ſting:</l>
               <l>For that they ſee</l>
               <l>the count call'd on at laſt:</l>
               <l>Which ſure on earth</l>
               <l>a hell may deemed be,</l>
               <l>When without mercy</l>
               <l>man his ſinnes deth ſee.</l>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:18516:113"/>
               <l>Thoſe men which onely</l>
               <l>to delights are given,</l>
               <l>At the approach of death</l>
               <l>doth feare and quake,</l>
               <l>What earth afforded</l>
               <l>they accounted heaven,</l>
               <l>And now perforce</l>
               <l>they muſt thoſe ioyes forſake,</l>
               <l>Gods bleſsings they</l>
               <l>moſt vildly have abus'd,</l>
               <l>And proffered time of Grace,</l>
               <l>they have refus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now thoſe words</l>
               <l>which <hi>ABRAHAM</hi> did ſay,</l>
               <l>To <hi>DIVES,</hi> when for water</l>
               <l>he did call;</l>
               <l>He findes too true</l>
               <l>whoſe ſmarts without alay,</l>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:18516:114"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:18516:114"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:18516:115"/>
               <l>His Sorrowes farre more better</l>
               <l>are then gall:</l>
               <l>His good things onely</l>
               <l>were upon this Earth,</l>
               <l>But life and them, are parted</l>
               <l>quite by death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Terrors and feares</l>
               <l>muſt needs their ſoules affright,</l>
               <l>When guilty Conſcience</l>
               <l>ſhowes Gods angry eye,</l>
               <l>O how they tremble!</l>
               <l>to approach that ſight,</l>
               <l>To whom their ſinne</l>
               <l>will out for vengeance cry;</l>
               <l>He who on earth</l>
               <l>to grieve, they did not feare,</l>
               <l>Will give a ſentence</l>
               <l>which their Soules will teare.</l>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:18516:115"/>
               <l>O how mans ſinnes</l>
               <l>that mild aſpect doth change,</l>
               <l>He, which for man did bleed</l>
               <l>doth man condemne,</l>
               <l>If by their ſinnes</l>
               <l>from the right path they range,</l>
               <l>Wanting their guide</l>
               <l>dangers approacheth them:</l>
               <l>The Woolfe once ſeazing</l>
               <l>'tis in vaine to flye,</l>
               <l>Theyr Shepheard heares not</l>
               <l>bootleſſe 'tis to cry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, who would this world</l>
               <l>as ought eſteeme,</l>
               <l>If truely he conſider</l>
               <l>every thing,</l>
               <l>Thoſe pleaſures which to man</l>
               <l>moſt happy ſeeme,</l>
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:18516:116"/>
               <l>Doth ſooneſt fade</l>
               <l>and gone they leave a ſting:</l>
               <l>Man vpon Earth</l>
               <l>no ſure abiding hath,</l>
               <l>Then feare betime</l>
               <l>before thou feele Gods wrath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>BELSHAZAR</hi> when hee was</l>
               <l>carrouſing ſet,</l>
               <l>Amongſt his Princes</l>
               <l>in his royall Throne;</l>
               <l>A writing turnes</l>
               <l>thoſe faire delights to Iet,</l>
               <l>A hand then ſhew'd</l>
               <l>makes bone incounter bone,</l>
               <l>He fearefull ſits</l>
               <l>whilſt thus it doth indite,</l>
               <l>Thou'rt weigh'd in ballance</l>
               <l>and art found too light,</l>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:18516:116"/>
               <l>Mans life's a ſceane</l>
               <l>and tragic ke wo's ſucceed,</l>
               <l>A Comet alwayes</l>
               <l>future harmes foretell,</l>
               <l>The happieſt life</l>
               <l>by death is made to bleed,</l>
               <l>If vnprepar'd he dye</l>
               <l>he goes to hell:</l>
               <l>The gate is ſhut,</l>
               <l>and they muſt take their lot,</l>
               <l>For 'twill be anſwered;</l>
               <l>loe, I know you not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto a thorney field</l>
               <l>and barren land,</l>
               <l>How fitly may mans life</l>
               <l>compared be,</l>
               <l>What cares, what feares,</l>
               <l>what griefes, are ſtill at hand,</l>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:18516:117"/>
               <l>And for one Ioy</l>
               <l>ten diſcontents we ſee:</l>
               <l>We alwayes walke</l>
               <l>as on a bridge of glaſſe,</l>
               <l>And oft it crakes</l>
               <l>as ouer it we paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Still barren is this world</l>
               <l>of true content,</l>
               <l>Fruitfull enough</l>
               <l>in procreating wees,</l>
               <l>Thorny afflictions</l>
               <l>towards vs are bent,</l>
               <l>But certaine Ioyes</l>
               <l>ſtill backwards from vs goes:</l>
               <l>Who thinkes to catch them</l>
               <l>doth a ſhadow chaſe,</l>
               <l>And like <hi>IXION</hi>
               </l>
               <l>doth a cloud embrace</l>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:18516:117"/>
               <l>Then why ſhould man</l>
               <l>thus waſte his precious time</l>
               <l>And triflingly let ſlip</l>
               <l>his golden dayes;</l>
               <l>O! turne to God,</l>
               <l>whilſt thou art in thy prime</l>
               <l>And put not off</l>
               <l>repentance with delayes:</l>
               <l>For when death comes</l>
               <l>it then will be too late,</l>
               <l>By teares or vowes</l>
               <l>for to prorogue thy ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Boaſt not of youth, or honours</l>
               <l>wealth, or ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Who truſts to them</l>
               <l>vpon a reede doth leane,</l>
               <l>The which be ſure</l>
               <l>deceiue thee will at length.</l>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:18516:118"/>
               <l>Then ſtrive from theſe vaine</l>
               <l>thy ſelfe to weane,</l>
               <l>And fill thy Lampe with oyle thoughts</l>
               <l>whil'ſt thou haſt ſpace,</l>
               <l>Leaſt afterward too late</l>
               <l>thou call for grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Breake off thy ſinnes</l>
               <l>by true repentant teares,</l>
               <l>And turne to God</l>
               <l>whilſt it is call'd to day,</l>
               <l>And reſt aſſured</l>
               <l>he their prayers heares,</l>
               <l>That vnto him</l>
               <l>vnceſſantly doe pray;</l>
               <l>For to incourage thee,</l>
               <l>he this did ſay,</l>
               <l>Who comes to me</l>
               <l>I will not caſt away.</l>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:18516:118"/>
               <l>Is not mans life</l>
               <l>compared vnto a flower,</l>
               <l>And, O how ſoone! alas,</l>
               <l>the ſame doth fade and dye,</l>
               <l>Then let man liue</l>
               <l>prepar'd (each day and houre)</l>
               <l>Leaſt vnawares</l>
               <l>the force of death he try:</l>
               <l>And beare this ſaying</l>
               <l>alwayes in thy minde;</l>
               <l>As death, thee leaves</l>
               <l>ſo Iudgement will thee find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the Flower</l>
               <l>in the chiefeſt prime,</l>
               <l>Doth fade and dye</l>
               <l>when Sun his face doth hide,</l>
               <l>For 'tis not in the earth's</l>
               <l>vaſt ſlippery clime,</l>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:18516:119"/>
               <l>An euer fading beeing</l>
               <l>to prouide:</l>
               <l>No more can ſtrength</l>
               <l>or skill preuaile at all,</l>
               <l>To lengthen life</l>
               <l>when God by death doth call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the ſpring</l>
               <l>the water forth doth put,</l>
               <l>And by the earth drunke vp</l>
               <l>no more is ſeene,</l>
               <l>So when by death</l>
               <l>our thrid of life is cut,</l>
               <l>On earth we are</l>
               <l>as we had neuer beene:</l>
               <l>Then whil'ſt we liue</l>
               <l>let's ſtriue to purchaſe Grace,</l>
               <l>That after Death</l>
               <l>in Heaven we may have place.</l>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:18516:119"/>
               <l>Alas! how many are</l>
               <l>the ſnares and bayts,</l>
               <l>Which Sathan layes,</l>
               <l>our poore ſoules to betray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>HIENA</hi> like,</l>
               <l>he murthers by deceites,</l>
               <l>Through falſe delights</l>
               <l>to cauſe us miſſe our way,</l>
               <l>His Mermaides Songs</l>
               <l>are onely ſweet in ſound,</l>
               <l>Approach them not,</l>
               <l>leſt Death thy life doth wound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore the ſafeſt way</l>
               <l>vnto our bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Is meditation</l>
               <l>of our certaine Death</l>
               <l>And though we tread</l>
               <l>the ſteps of carefulneſſe,</l>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:18516:120"/>
               <l>And all our life</l>
               <l>in ſorrow draw our breath,</l>
               <l>The guerdon of our paines</l>
               <l>our <hi>CHRIST</hi> will give</l>
               <l>In cauſing vs</l>
               <l>eternally to live.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus by a godly</l>
               <l>and an vpright life,</l>
               <l>Man of a deadly foe</l>
               <l>may make a friend</l>
               <l>And by a wiſe proviſion</l>
               <l>ſtint that ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Which Sathan laid</l>
               <l>to bring vs to our end:</l>
               <l>And though our fleſh</l>
               <l>prove falſe, our God is Iuſt,</l>
               <l>By death our ſoule</l>
               <l>gaines heauen, our body duſt.</l>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:18516:120"/>
               <l>Be ever vigilant</l>
               <l>in all thy wayes,</l>
               <l>And alwayes live</l>
               <l>as in the ſight of God,</l>
               <l>Performe good actions</l>
               <l>and vſe no delayes,</l>
               <l>Then feare not Death</l>
               <l>it brings with it no rod:</l>
               <l>With care attend</l>
               <l>that ſure vncertainety,</l>
               <l>And live, as euery howre</l>
               <l>thou ſhouldeſt dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This watchfull care</l>
               <l>wounds Sathan in the head,</l>
               <l>For hee that thinkes of Death</l>
               <l>doth ſhun all Sinne,</l>
               <l>By thought of this</l>
               <l>man to the world proves dead</l>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:18516:121"/>
               <l>He counts all droſſe</l>
               <l>and only <hi>CHRIST</hi> would win:</l>
               <l>No earthly Ioyes</l>
               <l>can cauſe him life to love,</l>
               <l>His Soule is fixt</l>
               <l>and nothing can him move.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus each weake Chriſtian</l>
               <l>may this tyrant foyle,</l>
               <l>For by <hi>CHRIST's</hi> Death</l>
               <l>man armed is with ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Though in this Combate</l>
               <l>he a while may toyle,</l>
               <l>But Faith in <hi>CHRIST,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>gives victory at length;</l>
               <l>And with a courage hold,</l>
               <l>man now may cry</l>
               <l>Death where's thy ſting?</l>
               <l>Grave where's thy victory?</l>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:18516:121"/>
               <l>What though we dye,</l>
               <l>as dye we ſurely muſt,</l>
               <l>Yet by this death,</l>
               <l>we now are gainers made.</l>
               <l>For when our bodyes</l>
               <l>are conſum'd to duſt,</l>
               <l>We ſhall be rais'd,</l>
               <l>from that Eternall ſhade:</l>
               <l>Our mortall bodyes,</l>
               <l>ſhall immortall be,</l>
               <l>And with our Soules,</l>
               <l>inioy Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our troubles in this life,</l>
               <l>now changed are;</l>
               <l>From tokens of his wrath,</l>
               <l>vnto his love.</l>
               <l>For though a while</l>
               <l>vpon the Earth me ſhare;</l>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:18516:122"/>
               <l>Of griefes and troubles,</l>
               <l>yet when God above:</l>
               <l>Shall by death call vs</l>
               <l>from the vaile of ſinne,</l>
               <l>Wee ſhall inioy.</l>
               <l>Eternall bliſſe with him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where all teares ſhall</l>
               <l>be wiped from our eyes,</l>
               <l>All griefes and ſorrowes</l>
               <l>then ſhall ended be,</l>
               <l>We ſhall be freed</l>
               <l>from all clamarous cries,</l>
               <l>No diſcontents nor troubles</l>
               <l>ſhall wee ſee:</l>
               <l>But Peace, and Ioyes</l>
               <l>and comforts ſhall be found,</l>
               <l>And alwayes in our eares</l>
               <l>a heavenly ſound.</l>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:18516:122"/>
               <l>Our Sences ſhall partake</l>
               <l>all of this Bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Our Eyes ſhall evermore</l>
               <l>behold our King,</l>
               <l>Our Hearing heavenly muſicke</l>
               <l>ſhall poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Our Tongues ſhall evermore</l>
               <l>his Praiſes ſing:</l>
               <l>Thus Smell, and Taſte,</l>
               <l>thus hands, and eares, and ſight,</l>
               <l>Shall evermore inioy</l>
               <l>a full delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto this Happineſſe</l>
               <l>and place of Ioy,</l>
               <l>In thy good time</l>
               <l>ſweet Saviour Chriſt vs bring,</l>
               <l>Where being freed</l>
               <l>from Sorrowes and annoy,</l>
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:18516:123"/>
               <l>Wee evermore</l>
               <l>thy bleſſed Praiſe may ſing:</l>
               <l>Where we ſhall never ceaſe</l>
               <l>but Night and Day,</l>
               <l>Sing Praiſe and Glory,</l>
               <l>vnto Thee alway.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18516:123"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
